<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations for regulating the excheqver in the more timely answering, better husbanding and more orderly and safe conduct of the revenues of the crown into His Majesties coffers, as hath been heretofore used by sheriffes : and for freeing the subject from all unjust vexations concerning the same : with the causes and remedies of the inconveniences which have been occasioned by the breach of the lawes and ancient course of the exchequer : as also for the better enabling and easing of sheriffes in the execution of their offices and passing their accompts / per C. Vernon ...</title>
            <author>Vernon, C. (Christopher)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5970</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13494358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13494358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 479:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations for regulating the excheqver in the more timely answering, better husbanding and more orderly and safe conduct of the revenues of the crown into His Majesties coffers, as hath been heretofore used by sheriffes : and for freeing the subject from all unjust vexations concerning the same : with the causes and remedies of the inconveniences which have been occasioned by the breach of the lawes and ancient course of the exchequer : as also for the better enabling and easing of sheriffes in the execution of their offices and passing their accompts / per C. Vernon ...</title>
                  <author>Vernon, C. (Christopher)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper, and are to be sold by Matth. Walbanke, Lan. Chapman, Wil. Cooke and Ric. Best,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Exchequer.</term>
               <term>Finance, Public --  England --  Accounting.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS For regulating the EXCHEQVER, In the more timely anſwering, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter husbanding, and more orderly and ſafe conduct of the Revenues of the Crown into his Majeſties Coffers, as hath been heretofore uſed by Sheriffes.</p>
            <p>And for freeing the Subject from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt vexations concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>With the Cauſes and Remedies of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences which have been occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the breach of the Lawes, and ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo for the better enabling and eaſing of Sheriffes in the execution of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and paſſing their Accompts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Per</hi> C. Vernon, <hi>de Scaccario Dom. Regis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Tho. Harper,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Matth. Walbanke, Lau. Chapman, Wil. Cooke,</hi> and <hi>Ric. Beſt.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR <hi>IOHN CVLPEPPER,</hi> Knight, Chancellor and Under-Treaſurer of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> 
               <hi>Exchequer,</hi> one of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> moſt honorable Privie Councell, and one of the Knights of the Shire for the County of Kent this Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honour,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have here adventured by the trueſt Copies I could meet withall, to doe my beſt in theſe times of wiſhed refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to repreſent and ſet foorth the portraiture of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> as it was in its firſt inſtitution and beſt perfection, ſo neere to the life as I could, ſitting ſo farre off; To the end it
<pb facs="tcp:99762:3"/>might, by a right underſtanding thereof, be reſtored to its ancient forme and proper working. In the deſcription whereof (as it was in its ſaid firſt inſtitution and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,) the great wiſedome and providence of our Anceſtors will appeare principally in theſe three points: Firſt, that no one Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer was to bee truſted alone in the receiving, charging, diſcharging, or iſſuing forth of the Kings Revenues: In that the <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>Great Roll</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> (being the <hi>Lord Treaſurers Roll)</hi> and of ſo great eſteeme in all ages, as that it hath been the Center and Repoſitory wherein to all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Crowne, as well in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> as from all other <hi>Courts,</hi> were and ſtill are to be reduced, was not intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> alone, but the <hi>Chancellor</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> by his Subſtitute or Deputy, is deſigned and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to write and keepe a double or counterpart thereof for controlment ſake.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point wherein their great wiſedome and care appeared, was, In that, as no Rent or Debt was to be charged in the ſaid <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>Great Roll,</hi> upon any the Kings Subjects, but by good and juſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Record, ſo the ſame (being once char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) was not to be diſcharged againe, or to
<pb facs="tcp:99762:3"/>bee ſet and poſted of <hi>de anno in annum,</hi> or otherwiſe <hi>prolonged,</hi> but by like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Record, leſt the ſame might thereby grow deſperate, or become a grievance to his Majeſties ſubjects.</p>
            <p>And the third and laſt point was, In that for avoyding of all ſuperfluous and un-neceſſary charge to the Crowne and ſubject, by having over-many hands in the Kings Purſe, they did provide and fore-ſee that the <hi>Exchequer</hi> ſhould not be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with moe perſons then was neceſſary: And to that end that the Sheriffe of every Shire and County ſhould bee the conſtant Miniſter for leavying and bringing in the Rents and Debts belonging to the Crowne.</p>
            <p>Which Rules, if they had been obſerved, and continued in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> according to their ſaid firſt inſtitution, many great loſſes and inconveniences which have beene occaſioned both to the King and Subject, by the breach and diſcontinuance thereof, might have been prevented, as in the inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe will appeare.</p>
            <p>The cauſes which moved me, at this time, (contrary to my my owne will and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as knowing my owne inſufficiencie) to publiſh this Treatiſe ſo unworthy of ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:99762:4"/>and ſo great a ſubject as this is, were prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally theſe which follow, namely:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that ſuch unperfect Copies upon this ſubject, as had at any time come to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall hands under my name, might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and put into ſome method of cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence conducing to the worke intended.</p>
            <p>A ſecond cauſe was, to give ſatisfaction to ſome of my neere friends, who by their importunities (over-haſtily before I could well deliberate thereof) thruſt mee forward to doe it, as conceiving I might give ſome light and furtherance thereby to the great worke intended for the eſtabliſhing and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of his Majeſties Revenue, and the cutting off and taking away the ſuperfluity of expences and abuſes of Officers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame.</p>
            <p>And in the laſt place, I was the rather induced to give way thereunto, in regard I ſpeake nothing of my ſelfe, but what I have authority for, either by good matter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> or from the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>That which now remaines on my part to be deſired, is, That your Honour being at this preſent (in the vacancie of a <hi>Lord Treaſurer)</hi> the chiefeſt Officer of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer;</hi> and one in whom his Majeſty
<pb facs="tcp:99762:4"/>(upon contemplation of your owne worth, hath repoſed ſo great a truſt and ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie over his Revenues) will be pleaſed ſo farre to patronize theſe poore Indeavours of mine, (howſoever performed with great weakneſſe and want of judgement) as (upon reading over the whole, and weighing the ſeverall Authorities, Proofes, and Reaſons, which are therein cited and ſet downe for warrant and confirmation thereof,) they may (for the matter) bee found worthy of your acceptation. And as there is a fitneſſe of Dedication from me in this kinde, due to your Honour, in reſpect of your high place and authority in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſo more particularly for your Noble favours alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed to mee and mine, whereby I am obliged, and muſt ever acknowledge my ſelfe to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble and devoted ſervant,</hi> Chriſtopher Vernon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="apology_for_errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:5"/>
            <p>Although the Printer uſed great diligence in the review and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his proves before hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſame to paſſe the Preſſe, yet becauſe he was not wel acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with my hand, nor with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer termes, ſome miſtakes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened one time when I was abſent, In regard whereof the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Reader for his better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of thoſe miſtakes and omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, is deſired that bee will firſt caſt his eye over the <hi>Errata</hi> in the end of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99762:5"/>
            <head>Conſiderations FOR <hi>Regulating the Exchequer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-51" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Court of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> is one of thoſe foure Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which,
<note place="margin">Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Kings Bench. Common Pleas, Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</note> in the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by the fundamentall lawes of this Realme, time beyond the memory of man. And for the due anſwering and managing of the <hi>Revenues</hi> of the Crown both certaine and caſual: The ſaid Court hath been ſupported with great and ancient priviledges and high authority by and under the ſurvey, rule and government of a Lord <hi>Treaſurer; Chancellor, Vnder-Treaſurer, Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99762:6"/>and <hi>Barons</hi> of the ſaid Court. And that the ſaid Court now is, and hath been anciently diſtinguiſhed and knowne by the <hi>Superior</hi> or <hi>Vpper,</hi> and the <hi>Inferior</hi> or <hi>Lower</hi> Exchequer. The Superior being alſo knowne by the Title of <hi>Scaccarium Computorum:</hi> And the lower by the Title of the <hi>Receit,</hi> where the Kings moneyes are paid to certaine Tellers, and Tallies ſtricken for the ſame, for diſcharge of ſuch <hi>Farmers, Debtors, Accountants,</hi> &amp;c. which pay in the ſame.</p>
               <p>The principall Officers of truſt in the ſaid ſuperior Exchequer (under the ſaid head Officers) are the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Lord Treaſurers Remembrancers,</hi> the <hi>Clerke of the Pipe,</hi> or Ingroſſer of the <hi>Great Roll,</hi> and the <hi>Controller</hi> of the Pipe, with a competent number of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors</hi> for preparing and caſting up all accounts. The ſaid <hi>Controller of the Pipe</hi> being to write a duplicate, or double of the ſaid great Roll, to remain in his cuſtody, for the better ſafeguard and controlment of the revenues of the Crowne; and twice every yeare, to make forth proces from the ſaid great Roll, to all <hi>Sheriffes</hi> for levying
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99762:6"/>the Rents, Farmes, and Debts in every Shire, City, and Towne Corporate; which proces was anciently called by the name of the <hi>Summons of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> being of the force and nature of <hi>a fieri facias,</hi> for levying of the Kings rents &amp; debts upon the goods &amp; chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of the Farmers and Debtors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpecified. Howbeit about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> 3. when the caſuall revenue, called the <hi>Greenwax,</hi> was ſo much encreaſed, that the Controller of the Pipe could not well undergo the burthen of the whole worke:
<note place="margin">Clerke of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreats.</note> There was a new Officer (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled the <hi>Clerke of the Eſtreats</hi>) intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to write the ſummons for the ſaid <hi>Greenwax,</hi> onely in aſſiſtance of the ſaid Controller: and one other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer called the <hi>Forraigne Appoſer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Forraigne appoſer.</note> For oppoſing of Sheriffes upon the ſaid Summons of Greenwax, who is, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with after every ſuch appoſall, to ſend the whole charge wherewith every Sheriffe chargeth himſelfe of the ſaid Greenwax, in every title into the <hi>Pipe,</hi> there to be added to the other charge of each Sheriffe upon his account in the great Roll, together with ſo much of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99762:7"/>every title as is to be charged upon the Lords and Bailiffes of Liberties; and that which is nichelled is to be written in proces a new from the Pipe, ſaving that the nichelled iſſues are by the <hi>Clerke of the Nichells</hi> ſent to the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Rememorancer, who according to the Statute of 27. <hi>E.</hi> 1. makes forth writs of <hi>Scire facias,</hi> out of his Office to all ſuch Sheriffes who returned thoſe parties at iſſues to ſhew cauſe why they ſhould not ſatisfie the ſame Iſſues to the King, by reaſon of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of the ſaid parties ſo by them returned at Iſſues: ſince which time of the introducing of the ſaid <hi>Clerke of the Eſtreats</hi> to write the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Greenwax, the ſummons written by the Controller of the Pipe, and the Clerke of the Eſtreats have been diſtinguiſhed by the names of the <hi>Summons of the Pipe,</hi> and <hi>Summons of the Greenwax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As concerning the ſaid caſuall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue called the <hi>Greenwax,</hi> it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of ſuch <hi>Fines, Iſſues, Amerciaments, Recognizances,</hi> for appearances and other forfeitures as are yearely ſet, loſt, and forfeited before the <hi>Juſtices of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99762:7"/>Kings Bench, Common Pleas, Barons</hi> of the Exchequer, <hi>Juſtices of Aſſize, Goale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deli cry, Juſtices of Peace, Commiſſioners of Sewers, Clerke of the Market,</hi> and the like; which (by the Lawes of this Kingdome) are to bee Eſtreat yearly, and ſent into the Exchequer, from all the ſaid Courts and places to the Lord Treaſurers <hi>Remembrancers</hi> Office, and from thence (after an entry made of the numbers of every ſcedule, &amp;c.) to bee forthwith delivered together with thoſe of the Exchequer (as well in that Office as in the Offices of the <hi>Kings Remembrancer</hi> and the <hi>Clerke of the Pleas</hi>) to the ſaid <hi>Clerke</hi> of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreats for execution to be done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in ſuch manner as is formerly ſet downe. And as for all <hi>Rents, Farmes, Cuſtodies, Extents,</hi> and other Debts and Duties belonging to the Crowne, as well the <hi>Remainders</hi> of the Farmes of the Counties, the <hi>Farmes of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeancies,</hi> and <hi>Aſſerts, the Farmes</hi> of Cities, Burroughes, and Townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, and <hi>all other Farmes</hi> and Rents, whatſoever whereof there is anſwere made yearly in the Exchequer, and all debts determined, and <hi>groſſe Debts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99762:8"/>from the Offices of the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers, whereof there is hope that ſomewhat ſhall be paid, and all debts and <hi>Supers</hi> depending in any accounts within the ſurvey of the ſaid Court of Exchequer. Theſe are by the new Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Exchequer,
<note place="margin">Stat. de Rutland, An. 10. E. 1.</note> called the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Rutland, An.</hi> 10. <hi>E.</hi> 1. to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>Great Roll</hi> of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> and proces to bee firſt made from thence to the Sheriffes by the <hi>Summons of the Pipe</hi> for leavying thereof to the Kings uſe accordingly.</p>
               <p>And the reaſons why the <hi>Summons of the Pipe</hi> (not extending to the body or lands of any debtor, but onely to their Goods and Chattels) and why the Summons of the Green Wax (not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending either to body or lands, or to the infringing or entring into any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty) is to be the firſt proces,
<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gna Charta, cap. 8.</note> is this: For that by the ſtatute of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> it is provided that no Sheriffe or Bailiffe ſhall ſeize any lands for the Kings debts, ſo long as the preſent Goods and Chattels of the debtor doe ſuffiſe, and the debtor himſelfe bee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſatisfie the ſame. And that the <hi>Pledges</hi> of the debtor ſhall not bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99762:8"/>as long as the principall debtor is ſufficient. And for that alſo if a ſtronger proceſſe ſhould bee firſt made to the Sheriffe of <hi>non omittas propter aliquem libertatem, &amp;c.</hi> For leavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Greene Wax, the Lords of liberties ſhould thereby bee barred and put by their Franchiſes and claimes, which would bee againſt common right.</p>
               <p>But they are much deceived that take the Summons of the Pipe to be no more then (as it were) a <hi>Scire fasias,</hi> or <hi>Summons</hi> to the Farmer or debtor to pay his rent or debt, or that it is but <hi>tardum remedium,</hi> or of ſlow execution to bring in the Kings Rents and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for though it is (in truth) but a Summons, yet it is a Summons (not to the debtor) but to the Sheriffe, and ſuch a Summons as tranſcends all other commands in any of the Kings Writs, for injoyning them to the performance of what is thereby required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Writ is as followeth:</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="writ">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>Carolus Dei gratia, &amp;c. </signed>
                        <salute>Vic. B. ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>vide ſicut teipſum &amp; omnia tua dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99762:9"/>quod ſis coram Theſaur. &amp; Baronum de Scaccario apud Weſtmonaſterium in Craſtino clauſi Paſche prox. futur. Et habeas ibi tunc quicquid nobis debes de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis &amp; veteribus firmis &amp; omnia debita ſubſcript. &amp; hanc ſummon. de Pipa. </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte A. B. Theſaur. Angliae apud Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterium <date>duodecimo die Februarii, Anno, &amp;c.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>As if the King ſhould ſay,
<note place="margin">Viz. at the Eaſter proffer by the firſt Summons, and at the Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by the ſecond.</note> Mr. Sheriffe, as you love your ſelfe, your wife and children, and all that you have, ſee that you bee upon ſuch a day at Weſtminſter, before our Treaſurer and Barons, and bring with you all our Farms and rents then due, and all other the debts under-written, and this Summons.</p>
               <p>And if there were no more in it but this (it being of ſo great antiquity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the memory of man) as makes it of ſufficient force by the Common lawes of this Kingdome to bee obeyed: yet this is not all; for this Writ is ſtrongly backed by an Act of Parliament in <hi>Anno</hi> 51, <hi>H.</hi> 3. called the <hi>Statute of the Exchequer,</hi> whereby it is ordained, that all <hi>Sheriffs, Farmers, Bailiffs,</hi> of <hi>Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and others ſhall come to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99762:9"/>
                  <hi>proffers</hi> of the Exchequer the Munday after the <hi>utas of Eaſter,</hi> and the Munday after the Feaſt of S. <hi>Michael</hi> to pay the Farmes, Rents and Iſſues belonging to the King, and ſhall bring at the foreſaid Termes, the Farms Rents &amp; Iſſues due, wholly into the <hi>Exchequer:</hi> And if they make default, their bodies ſhall remain without departing from thence, untill they have paid or made agreement; and he that wil not come at the Termes aforeſaid, ſhall bee amerced after the cuſtome of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes and Bailiffes at the ſame Termes ſhall bring and pay ſuch moneyes as they have received of the <hi>Summons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and other the Kings debts; and ſhall bee prepared to make full account of the things aforeſaid, to the Treaſurer and Barons of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</hi> And this is in all points agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Summons of the Pipe,</hi> directed to the Sheriffes twice in the yeare, for bringing the Farms, Rents &amp; Debts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the King, at the times in the ſaid Statute mentioned; and hath been in uſe ever ſince the making of the ſaid ſtatute, and is ſo continued at this day (though not rightly put in execution.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99762:10"/>The firſt Summons now ſent forth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare to the Sheriffes being under the <hi>Teſte</hi> of 12. <hi>Feb.</hi> which is the laſt day of Hillary Tearme, returnable in <hi>Craſt. clauſ. paſche prox. futur.</hi> (being the Eaſter proffer) ſtiled in the ſaid Statute to be the Munday after the <hi>utas</hi> of Eaſter; and the other Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons bearing alway the <hi>Teſte</hi> of the laſt day of every Trinity Tearme retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in <hi>Craſt. Mich.</hi> (if it be not Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day) which before is mentioned to be the Munday after the feaſt of Sain <hi>Michael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Sheriffes have ſo made their appearances at their Eaſter and Michaelmas proffers (as aforeſaid) and brought in and paid at his Majeſties receit ſo much at each proffer, as was then come, or lawfully might have come to their hands, or in default thereof have beene amerced or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ward, every Sheriffe is to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in perſon at his day of prefixion in the Exchequer before the Treaſurer and Barons of the ſaid Court, or (if he be hindred by ſickneſſe) before ſome Commiſſioners thereunto authoriſed by the Court, to make his finall account
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99762:10"/>of all the iſſues and profits of his office due to the King for his yeare, and then is to take his oath as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he ſhall yeeld to his Majeſty a true and lawfull acount of the iſſues and profits of his ſaid office of Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, and make true anſwer to the <hi>Summons</hi> of the <hi>Pype</hi> and <hi>Greenwax,</hi> and in the ſame account to charge himſelfe with all ſuch ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as he, his Vnder-Sheriffe, Bayliffs or Miniſters for him have levied, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully might have levied to his Majeſties uſe by the Summons aforeſaid: And of all <hi>Fellones</hi> goods, <hi>outlawed</hi> mens goods, <hi>attainted</hi> mens goods, <hi>wayfes, eſtraies,</hi> and other profits whatſoever which have come to the hands of his Vnder-Sheriffe, Bayliffes or Miniſters by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his ſaid office: And that he ſhall not in the ſame account vouch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny franchiſes or liberties, nor make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny petition, nor aske any allowance or diſcharge, but ſuch as ſhall bee good and true, and likewiſe to deliver a book written in parchment, declaring of whom and where he receiveth the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condells,</hi> and other the Rents and Farmes written unto him in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99762:11"/>of the Pipe, and well and truly to behave himſelfe in yeelding the ſame account, as a true accountant ought to doe without any omiſſion or concealment.</p>
               <p>And every Sheriffe which ſhall not ſo appeare at his ſaid day of prefixion before the Treaſurer and Barons, and take his oath, or procure ſuch commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for taking thereof at the ſame time as aforeſaid, ſhall forfeit to the King 5. pounds for every day after his ſaid day of prefixion, that he ſhall ſo faile to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and take his ſaid oath as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and after the taking of the ſaid oath every Sheriffe is to attend upon the Court, and to be appoſed before the ſaid Treaſurer and Barons in open Court upon the ſaid Summons of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> and ſhall according to his ſaid oath charge himſelfe with all ſuch Farmes, Rents, and other debts writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unto him by the ſaid Summons of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> as he hath or lawfully might have levyed. And to ſuch Farmes, Rents and Debts as he chargeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe withall,
<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer and clarke of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are in like manner to marke the one the sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and the other the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord upon their appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall on the greeen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wax.</note> 
                  <hi>tot</hi> or <hi>on<hi rend="sup">i</hi> (ſcilicet oneratur niſi)</hi> is to be marked againſt their names and Summons, by the Clarke of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99762:11"/>
                  <hi>Pipe,</hi> and controller reſpectively in the ſaid great Rolle, and <hi>Counter Rolle,</hi> and to be entred, and caſt up in his charge in the ſaid great Rolle by the firſt <hi>Secondary</hi> of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> together with the whole charge of his forraigne Account and Greenwax, as is before obſerved, and the ſaid Sheriffe to pay and anſwer to the King all and every part thereof which ſhall remaine due upon the foot of his account, and not by him formerly paid, and anſwered at his ſaid proffers, except onely there ſhall be ſome good cauſe of diſcharge by matter of Record, or order to bee made in open Court for any of thoſe wherewith hee ſo charged himſelfe with <hi>on<hi rend="sup">i</hi>
                  </hi> as aforeſaid: And to ſuch as he ſhall averre to be illeviable or to bee dead, or within any liberty ſo as hee could not levy the ſame by his ſaid Summons <hi>Nichell diem clauſit extrem.</hi> or ſuch, or ſuch a <hi>liberty,</hi> are to be in like manner marked againſt their names and ſummes; and thoſe that are ſo returned with <hi>Nichil</hi> or <hi>diem clauſit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem.</hi> to be forthwith to be put into <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula pipe,</hi> and ſent to the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Remembrancers Office, ſo as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99762:12"/>ſtronger Proces to the next Sheriffe may be made from thence againſt their bodies, lands and goods for levying thereof to his Majeſties uſe, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to be made from thence to faithfull and circumſpect men of every County for making inquiry into the ſame,
<note place="margin">Weſtm. 1. An. 3. E 1. cap. 19. Stat. An. 6. H. 4. c. 3.</note> according to former Statutes in that behalfe provided: And if upon returne of the ſaid Commiſſions it ſhall appeare to the Court that any of the ſaid parties by whom any ſuch debts are owing, are nothing worth, and that their debts are deſperate, they are (according to the foreſaid new Statute of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> called the Statute of <hi>Rutland</hi>) in eaſe of Sheriffes to be removed out of the ſaid <hi>Annual</hi> or great <hi>Rolle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stat. de Rutland anno 10. E 1.</note> into an <hi>exannual Rolle,</hi> and not to be written any more in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Sheriffes, but to be onely yearly read upon their accounts to ſee which of them may be revived, and ſuch as are like to be ſo revived and made good to bee reinſerted into the ſaid <hi>Annuall Rolle</hi> for new Proces to be made thereupon as the caſe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; and if upon returne of the ſaid Commiſſions it ſhall appeare that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99762:12"/>the Sheriffe (or any for him) hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any of the ſaid Farms or debts, and concealed the ſame upon his account, the ſaid Sheriffe is according to the ſaid Statute of <hi>Weſtmin. Anno</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 19.
<note place="margin">Stat de Weſtm. An. 3. E. 1 cap. 19.</note> to make anſwer thereof to the King, and to pay to the party grieved thrice ſo much as he received, and to make fine at the Kings pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And the like Commiſſions are to be awarded into every County after the determination of every account in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> by <hi>Sheriffes, Eſcheators,
<note place="margin">Stat. anno 6. H. 4. c. 3.</note> Aulvegours, Cuſtomers, Controllers,</hi> &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings Officers, and acoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants concealing and receiving to their owne uſe that which rightfully apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the King, for inquiry to be made thereof: And in caſe the ſaid Accountants upon returne of the ſaid Commiſſions be found guilty of any ſuch frauds and deceits, they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre treble the ſame to the King, and their bodies to priſon, untill they have made fine &amp; ranſome to the King after the diſcretion of the Iudges.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the ſeverall ſummes of money wherewith the Sheriffes ſhall ſo charge themſelves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99762:13"/>upon their accounts in the ſaid <hi>Annual Rolle,</hi> they are not to depart the Court (without ſpeciall licence of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer and Barons, untill they have fully paid and ſatisfied the ſame,
<note place="margin">In libro ordin. ex parte Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merator. Theſaur. Term. H. l. Anno 32. Eliz.</note> or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a diſcharge or <hi>Exon. de Anno</hi> for the ſame, upon good matter of Record, or order in open Court: And upon the final determination of their ſaid Accounts, the ſaid Sheriffes whole charge and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge is to be read and caſt up in open Court, before the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> &amp; <hi>Barons</hi> of the ſaid Court, in the preſence of the <hi>Treaſurers Remembrancer, Clerk of the Pipe, Controller,</hi> &amp; other Officers whom it ſhall or may concern; and two <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> at the leaſt for caſting up the ſaid accounts: And what every of the ſaid Sheriffes ſhall be found in debet upon his ſaid account (all his Tallies, Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and juſt Petitions deducted) the ſaid Sheriffe is forthwith to pay to the King before hee bee diſmiſſed out of Court, or to be committed to ward un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he pay the ſame.</p>
               <p>And if any Sheriffe after his ſaid Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, and charging himſelfe with the paticular ſummes aforeſaid, ſhall depart the Court (without ſpeciall licence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99762:13"/>before he hath fully perfected his ſaid Accompt, and is ſo delivered out of Court, as aforeſaid, his goods &amp; lands are to be ſeized into the Kings hands <hi>nomine diſtrictionis,</hi> and the King to take the iſſues and benefit thereof, without any part to goe in deduction of his debt, or a <hi>Serjeant at Armes</hi> to be ſent for ſuch delinquent Sheriff, who (if hee bee no priviledged perſon) is to be brought up and committed to Ward until he ſhall fully perfect his accompt, and pay or diſcharge what is juſtly due thereupon, as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>In like manner,
<note place="margin">Lords of Liberties, Maiors, Bailiffes, &amp;c.</note> all <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes</hi> of <hi>Liberties, Maiors,</hi> &amp;c. are to appeare at the ſaid proffers at Eaſter and Michaelmas, and at the times by the Court prefixed to perfect and finiſh their Accounts for all ſuch moneyes as they ſtand charged withall; and to pay what is due to the Crowne over and beſides their juſt allowances, and what they can by their claimes, or for default thereof, their bodies to remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out departing, and their liberties to bee ſeized into the Kings hands.</p>
               <p>And as concerning ſuch ſummes of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99762:14"/>money as by the <hi>Awards</hi> of the Court ſhall be put into <hi>Cedula Pipe</hi> for ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger proces to bee made by the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Remembrancer in regard of a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em clauſ. extrem.</hi> or the like, the ſaid Treaſurers Remembrancer is forthwith at the next <hi>Liberate</hi> or <hi>Sealing</hi> day, to make forth the ſtrongeſt proces to the Sheriffes (as the caſe ſhall require) for leavying thereof; wherein by the long writ <hi>(called the Prerogative Writ</hi>) the Sheriff hath power to enquire (if the debtor bee dead) to whoſe hands his goods and Chattels are come,
<note place="margin">The long Writ cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Writ, out of the Treaſurers Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers Office, un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Teſte of the chiefe Baron.</note> and to put the ſame in ſafe cuſtody for the King (who is to be firſt ſatisfied;) and if he had any lands, what lands he had at the time he ſo firſt came indebted, or at any time after, and to whoſe hands the ſame are come, and to make ſeiſure thereof. And if the debtor be living, to leavy the debt upon his or their goods or lands; or for default therof <hi>(Magnat. Dominis &amp; dominabus exceptis)</hi> to attach his or their body, with ſuch other ſtrong Clauſes for leavying thereof, as can bee deviſed. And the Tearme fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, the Sheriffes are to be appoſed upon all thoſe Writs which were ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99762:14"/>ſent forth for debts in <hi>Cedula Pipe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Barons of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer Chamber;</hi> and if the Barons can finde or learne that the Sheriffes have uſed any negligence or conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence in executing their ſaid Writs, they do uſually amerce the ſaid Sheriffs according to their defaults, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſet a paine on their heads, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they pay or ſhew good cauſe of diſcharge or do better ſervice by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day: In all which cauſes the ſaid amerciaments ſo ſet or incurred, are forthwith to be ſent downe into the Pipe for proces to be made thereupon accordingly.</p>
               <p>And the ſaid Treaſurers Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer doth in like manner recover ſuch amerciaments as are ſo impoſed by the Court, and ſuch reliefes as are belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the King after the death of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon dying ſeiſed by whom ſuch reliefes are due, and ſuch ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as any Sheriffe ſhall charge himſelf withall by way of <hi>fieri feci,</hi> and the like; as alſo all ſuch extents and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates of the goods, and two parts of the lands of <hi>Recuſants</hi> as are found by Inquiſitions, all which the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99762:15"/>Remembrancer doth in like manner ſend downe into the <hi>Pipe</hi> to be put in charge in the ſaid great Rolle, and prepares the <hi>originalls</hi> ſent into his Office from the Chancery, and therein markes <hi>Ingroſſat.</hi> againſt all ſuch Rents as are reſerved upon any grants in Fee Farme, or upon any other Farms or cuſtodies for tearme of life, or years, or for ſo long time as the ſame ſhall continue in the Kings hands, for the ſaid Clarke of the Pipe to draw downe from thence yearly to be put in charge in the ſaid great Rolle, after the title of <hi>Nova oblata.</hi> And the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers Remembrancer out of his Office makes forth <hi>Writs of Diſtringas</hi> to all Sheriffes againſt the Kings tenants for preſerving of his Majeſties tenures and ſervices,
<note place="margin">Writers of Diſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas.</note> and the Iſſues thereupon returned by the ſaid Sheriffes in every Shire, certifieth to the Clarke of the <hi>Eſtreats</hi> twice in the yeare to bee by him ſent forth to the Sheriffes in the Summons of the Greenwax: And for the fines due to the King for reſpiting the homage of his tenants, the ſaid Treaſurers Remembrancer chargeth himſelfe with all thoſe fines which are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99762:15"/>drawne into the Pipe, and by him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered unto the receit, as alſo for all the Caſtle ward rents in ſeverall Counties payable to the Caſtle of <hi>Dover, Stat. anno</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. And the Kings Majeſties Remembrancer in his Office recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all fines and other debts ſent into his Office out of any other Court, and recovereth all ſuch <hi>Recognizances, Amerciaments, fi. fac.</hi> of <hi>Sheriffes</hi> moyties of <hi>forfeitures</hi> about <hi>cuſtome</hi> cauſes or upon <hi>penall Lawes,</hi> and the like, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Records thereof into the Pipe, and alſo of ſuch Bonds and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations as are forfeited and recovered for the King, to be from thence drawn downe and charged for his Majeſties ſervice in the ſaid great Rolle: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo maketh forth the writs of <hi>Diſtringas</hi> againſt all Accomptants, whoſe names are to be entred upon the <hi>States</hi> of Accomptants in his Office, as well the Maſter of the horſe, the keeper of the Warderob, Treaſurer of the Chamber, Treaſurer at Warres, Treaſurer of the Navy, collectors of Subſidies and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and all receivers of the Kings Revenues, and other Accomptants whatſoever, who are to make their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99762:16"/>accompts in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and againſt ſuch as have had any money <hi>impreſted</hi> to them for the Kings ſpeciall ſervice, and the like, &amp; to ſee Iſſues returned againſt them untill they ſhall perfect their ſaid accompts before the ſeverall Auditors thereunto aſſigned, and enter the ſame upon the Rolle of the States of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptant in his Office, and before the Treaſurers Remembrancer upon the Rolle of <hi>Viewes</hi> in his Office, from whence the ſaid accompts after they are declared before the Treaſurers and Barons of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and ſo entred as aforeſaid, are alſo to be ſent into the Pipe, there to remaine as the Kings and Subjects evidence upon record for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; as alſo to the end Proces may bee made from thence for ſuch <hi>ſupers</hi> and <hi>debts</hi> as are therein depending. And all ſuch Iſſues as are loſt by any of the ſaid Accomptants for their not accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in due time, and by the Sheriffes returned upon the ſaid Writs of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringas</hi> ſent from the ſaid Office of the Kings Remembrancer, are in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner twice in the yeare to be eſtreated to the ſaid Clarke of the Eſtreates, to be by him ſent forth in the Summons
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99762:16"/>of the Greenewax accordingly. In his Office alſo is kept the red Booke of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> being an excllent Treatiſe of the ancient Rolles and Lawes of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> conceived to be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Gervaſius Tilburienſis, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re H.</hi> 2. which book is commonly ſent by the Curſiter Baron into the Kings Bench and Common Pleas, or in the Tearme time to remove any matter ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there againſt any Officer, Miniſter or ſervitor of theirs, or any Accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant there that prayeth his priviledge in due time, upon which red booke ſo ſhewed, and the party teſtified by the Baron to be of that Court as aforeſaid, his priviledge is uſually allowed. And both the ſaid Remembrancers doe make forth copies to the Auditors of all Seiſures made by Sheriffes for any debts, or by reaſon of any <hi>Alienations, Outlawries,</hi> or other duties to the King, upon the writs ſent out of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to be by the ſaid Auditors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively charged in the ſaid Sheriffes forraine accompts. In which their ſaid forraine accompts the ſaid Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors which take theſe accompts are to enter the particulars where with every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99762:17"/>Sheriffe chargeth himſelfe for the goods and chattells of <hi>fellones outlawed</hi> and attainted perſons, <hi>waifes, eſtraies</hi> and the like according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for that there may be ſome juſt cauſe of diſcharge of the Sheriffe and debtor by an abſolute <hi>exo.</hi> or of the Sheriffe for his yeare by an <hi>exo. de anno</hi> of ſome part of the Seiſures and Iſſues charged in his ſaid forraine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, or of ſome other part of the debts or farmes charged upon him in the ſaid great Roll of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> or of ſome part of the Greenwax moncies charged upon him by the ſaid forraine Appoſer as aforeſaid; as for inſtance: There may be ſome juſt cauſe for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Sheriffe and debtor by an abſolute <hi>exo.</hi> upon his accompt of ſome ſeiſure, debt or duty charged upon the ſaid Sheriffe as aforeſaid, in regard there was a preconveiance of the land by the debtor <hi>bona fide</hi> before the debt grew due to the King, or that the debt or duty for which the ſaid ſeiſure was made is fully ſatisfied and anſwered to the Crowne; or for that the like debt or duty it ſelfe is abſolutely to bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99762:17"/>diſcharged by plea &amp; judgement, giſt or grant from the Crowne or by ſome other good matter of record: And as there may be juſt cauſe for an abſolute <hi>exo.</hi> to the Sheriffe and debtor, ſo there may be as juſt cauſe for an <hi>exo. de anno</hi> to the Sheriffe upon his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of ſome of the ſeiſures and debts charged upon him as aforeſaid, either in regard the lands in ſeiſure are in the Kings hands by reaſon of the <hi>minority</hi> of the heire or owner of the ſaid lands, or for that the ſaid lands were made in <hi>Iointure</hi> or in <hi>Leaſe</hi> for terme of yeares or life before the debt grew due, or the like, in all which ſeverall caſes the <hi>Lord Treaſurers Remembrancer</hi> upon ſight of ſuch good matter of record, or other ſuch juſt cauſe allowed of by the Court as aforeſaid, is (upon the deſire and petition of the Sheriffe to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged thereof upon his accompt) to rule ſeverall petitions to every She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe upon his or their ſaid accompts reſpectively for an abſoute <hi>exo.</hi> or an <hi>exo. de anno</hi> for the ſame as the caſe ſhall require, which is to be by him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and ſet downe to every petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on accordingly; howbeit the ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99762:18"/>Treaſurers Remembrancer is not to rule any ſuch petition for an abſolute <hi>exon.</hi> or <hi>exon. de anno</hi> to any Sheriffe of or for any Seiſure, Farme, Debt, or other ſumme of money whatſoever, but of ſuch onely as ſhall fully appeare to him, either by the Sheriffes forraine accompt it ſelfe, or by ſome Conſtat or Certificate in parchment under the hands of the Clerke of the Pipe, or Clerke of the Eſtreats reſpectively, to be part of the Sheriffes charge ſo charged upon him in his accompt in the ſaid great Roll; for that if ſuch petition ſhould be allowed to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of any ſumme, being no part of his charge, the King ſhould loſe and bee defrauded of ſo much thereby.</p>
               <p>Moreover the ſaid Lord Treaſurers Remembrancer doth upon Certificate from the Iuſtices of Aſſize (ratified and allowed under the hand of the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaſurer of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> for the time being) rule petitions for allowance to Sheriffes upon their accompts for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage or removing of priſoners, repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Gaols and other extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſervices done by Sheriffes in the time of their Sheriffwicke: All which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99762:18"/>petitions are by the ſaid Treaſurers Remembrancer to bee entred upon Record in his Office, and to be ſent to the Clerk of the Pipe (for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) to bee entred and allowed upon each Sheriffes accompt reſpectively in the ſaid Annuall or great Roll of the Pipe, in deduction of ſo much of each Sheriffes charge, ſo as one Record may bee diſcharged by another, according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here (by the way) is to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the ſaid Clerke of the Pipe is not, nor ought not, to diſcharge or ſet off from any Sheriffe, any Farme, debt, or other ſumme of money what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever charged upon him in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in the ſaid great Roll, but ſuch onely as ſhall appeare to bee paid into his Majeſtis Receipt of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> by Tallies to bee joyned and allowed in the ſaid Roll,
<note place="margin">Statut. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1 R. 2 cap. 5.</note> or ſuch as ſhall appeare to be diſcharged or ſet off by ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Record as is laid downe in the Sheriffes ſeverall petitions, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; nor to give any allowances to Sheriffes upon their ſaid accompts, but ſuch as ſhall either bee warranted by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99762:19"/>Tallies, <hi>de</hi> Regard, to bee ſevied in his Majeſties ſaid Receipt of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or by ſome judgement of Court en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or to bee entred in one of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers Offices: And if hee doe otherwiſe, the <hi>Controller</hi> of the Pipe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or at the Sheriffs caſting out of Court, is to informe the Court there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo as the ſaid undue diſcharges and miſallowances may bee certified and made void. And if the ſaid Controller, either through ignorance or conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence, ſhall not diſcharge the truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in him therein, hee ſhall bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for his conſent in like manner as hee that admitted of ſuch falſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances, &amp;c. and as he that tooke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance thereof: namely, to pay ſo much to the King,
<note place="margin">Stat. do Scaccorio Anno 51. H 3.</note> as the allowance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted unto: To bee impriſoned a yeare and forty dayes, and to bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the Kings pleaſure.</p>
               <p>But hereunto may be objected, that if the Clerk of the Pipe be to give no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to Sheriffs upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their accounts, but of ſuch moneyes onely for which Tallies are ſtricken in his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and of ſuch ſummes as are to bee allowed, ſet off, or diſcharged by judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99762:19"/>of Court, or ſuch matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord as is aforeſaid: How comes it then to paſſe that allowance hath been given to Shiriffes upon their accompts in the ſaid <hi>great Roll</hi> from time to time, by acquittances of Noble men for their <hi>Creation moneyes</hi> payable by Sheriffes out of the profits of their Counties, and the like; and by acquittances of ſuch Receivers to whom the King hath granted the receipt of the yearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, ariſing of any certain or caſuall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue within the Sheriffes charge. To which is anſwered, That the allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given by the acquittances of Noble men and others, for ſuch ſummes of mony as are payable to them by She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes out of the profits of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (being to their owne uſe) are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes warranted by judgement of Court, before any ſuch allowance is to be given: And as to the allowance of Acquittances for moneyes of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aforeſaid, paid or to bee paid by Sheriffes to Receivers as aforeſaid to the Kings uſe, ſuch Acquittances are not (in truth) to bee allowed by the courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> but by Tallies of aſſignment to be firſt ſtricken in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99762:20"/>Receipt for the ſame, in ſuch ſort as is uſed at this day for his Majeſties Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe and Houſhold, and for the poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines, Iſſues of Iurors, and the like, there being no ſuch controlment for Acquittances,
<note place="margin">Much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances, then Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</note> as is for Tallies, and it being much more eaſie to counterfeit <hi>Acquittances</hi> then Tallies; albeit even Tallies have been counterfeited to the loſſe and prejudice of the Crowne, which could not bee diſcovered before they were rejoyned with their foyles, according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> Beſides, the Subject which really payes his mony to a Receiver to the Kings uſe, &amp; takes his Acquittance for it, runnes a greater hazard to pay the ſame money againe in caſe ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance be loſt, and that the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doe not ſatisfie the ſame upon his Accompt, which hazard is avoided by ſtriking a Tally for the ſame in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Receipt, which is alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant upon Record for the parties diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, in caſe the Tally it ſelfe bee loſt.</p>
               <p>And as it is to be noted, that the Clerk of the Pipe is not to diſcharge or ſet off any part of the Sheriffes charge, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99762:20"/>by Tallies to be leavied in his Majeſties Receipt of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> judgement of Court, or ſuch matter of Record, as is before mentioned; ſo it may bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe obſerved, that the Treaſurers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer is not to rule any petition upon the Sheriffes Accompts for debt, recognizance, or other duty belonging to his Majeſty, wherewith the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes have charged themſelves upon their accompts, but by matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, or order in open Court, and not upon any other warrant whatſoever, which is not grounded upon ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Record, or order in open Court,
<note place="margin">Inter or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din. term. Hilar. an. 32. Eliz. Reg. ez parte Rem. Theſaur.</note> as aforeſaid. For if way ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Sheriff, to ſet off or diſcharge himſelfe upon his accompt of the farmes, debts, or ſummes of money by him taken into his charge at his appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, upon ordinary ſuggeſtions that hee could not leavie the ſume, or by reaſon of the poverty of the debtor, or in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the ſubject to eaſe him from the rigor and penalty which the Law hath inflicted upon him for ſome offence, (which is onely in the Kings power to mitigate or remit) or upon any other ground then by matter of Record, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99762:21"/>order in open Court, as aforeſaid, then it would follow, that the greateſt part of the Sheriffes totts and ſummes of money by him taken in charge at his appoſals, would be ſet off and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſo his appoſals would bee of no force or vertue, which by the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent courſe of the Court, bindes him to anſwer the ſame to the King, unleſſe ſome juſt cauſe be ſhewed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as afore is ſaid: ſeeing he might (at his choyce) have totted or nichel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſame at his ſaid appoſals; and then alſo would follow, that the King ſhould be diveſted of the grace which properly belongs to himſelfe for miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating and remitting of ſuch forfeitures and penalties to his ſubjects as the caſe ſhall require, which the late Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> (of famous memory) for the moſt part kept in her owne power for gratifying her loving ſubjects withall, by a generall pardon of grace at every Parliament.</p>
               <p>Thus much may ſuffice to have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the ſuperiour or upper Court of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> touching the ancient courſe of paſſing Accompts by Sheriffes and other Accomptants.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99762:21"/>
               <p>In the next place, before I paſſe from the ſuperiour <hi>Exchequer</hi> called <hi>Scacca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinm Computorum,</hi> to the lower called the <hi>Receipt:</hi> It will not be amiſſe to take a ſhort view of the Officers there, and in whoſe gifts their Offices are.</p>
               <p>And firſt for the Lord <hi>Treaſurer and Chancellor,</hi> their places are as anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vnder-Treaſurer</hi> or <hi>Vice-Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> was not knowne till the time of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. at which time the Lord Treaſurers Remembrancer was made <hi>Vice-Treaſurer,</hi> and whether of the Kings nomination or the Treaſurers, is not knowne. Sir <hi>Iohn Baker</hi> being nominated Vice-Treaſurer in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. had a patent from the King of the ſaid Office, under the great Seal, which is ſtill in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>chiefe Baron</hi> and three other learned Barons, and the Puny or Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor Baron are all in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Curſitor Baron</hi> being ſo called becauſe he is choſen moſt uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of ſome of the beſt experienced Clerkes of the two Remembrancers, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99762:22"/>Clerke of the Pipes Office, and is to informe the Bench and the Kings lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſell from time to time, both in Court and out of Court, what the courſe of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the ſame, and of the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative and benefit which his Majeſty hath thereby which the courſe of the Court moſt commonly maintaineth and reſpecteth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>two Chanoberlaines</hi> had in old time great Authority in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and have kept the keyes of the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Coffers, and were ever privy to the pells of <hi>Introitus &amp; exitus,</hi> of the which each of them are to keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement at this day, and anciently no money was iſſued out of the receit without their privity, their names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill continued in all privy Seales for payment of money out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, though it is now delivered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. Their place in Court is next to the Barons, and they may ſit &amp; keep their places daily in Court if they like to attend and hearken to the cauſes there without any intermedling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in But at the election of the Sheriffes <hi>Craſtino animarum</hi> they uſe to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99762:22"/>and may ſay their opinion for preferment or ſtay of men to be She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, as the Barons and Iuſtices do. Their places were anciently of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, but now are in the Kings guift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Kings Majeſties Attorney and Sollicitor generall</hi> have beene alwaies reckoned amongſt the Officers of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> though they have audience and come within the barre in all other Courts, their places being in the Kings guift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Kings Rememcrancers</hi> Office hath alwayes ſince the firſt erection been in the Kings guift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Treaſurers Remembrancers</hi> Office implies by the title that it hath beene in the Lord Treaſurers guift, but for a long time it hath been and now is in the Kings guift.</p>
               <p>The Office of <hi>the Clerke of the Pipe,</hi> or ingroſſer of the great Rol, was anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently in the Lord Treaſurers guift till about the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. ſince which time it hath beene and now is in the Kings guift.</p>
               <p>The Office of the <hi>Controller</hi> of the Pipe is at this day and alwayes hath
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99762:23"/>beene in the gift of the Chancellor of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> the ſaid Controller be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anciently ſtiled <hi>Clericus Cancellar.</hi> and the Clerke of the Pipe <hi>Clericus Theſſ.</hi> and <hi>Cancellarius</hi> was and is ſtill written upon the Controllers Roll <hi>&amp; Theſ.</hi> anciently upon the great Roll, to diſtinguiſh between them: And for that reaſon, ſome have been of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Chancellor ſits above the Lord Treaſurer in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> Court, becauſe of his ſuperintendency and controlement over his Roll.</p>
               <p>The office of the <hi>Remembrancer</hi> of the firſt fruits and tenthes in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Surveior generall</hi> of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties lands, &amp;c. in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Clerke of the Pleas</hi> in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>forraine Appoſer</hi> and <hi>Clerke of the Eſtreats</hi> in the Lord Treaſurers gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>two Auditors</hi> of the impreſts, in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſeven Auditors</hi> of the Revenew, who have in charge before them the Revenew annexed to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> upon the diſſolution of the Augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99762:23"/>Court, <hi>anno</hi> 1. <hi>Mariae Reg.</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the receivers generall make their accompts according to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſignments by their letters patents under the great Seale from the King. The other buſineſſes which belongs to their places as they are <hi>Auditors,</hi> or Clerkes in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> for taking the accompts of <hi>Sheriffes, Eſcheators, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers, Controllers, Collectors</hi> of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies,</hi> the <hi>Cofferers Accompt,</hi> and the like, they have them by aſſignment from the <hi>Marſhall</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> from time to time in open Court, and ſo entred in his booke, to the intent no accomptant ſhould take an Auditor of his owne choice. Their places are in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Auditor and Receivor</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the <hi>Dutchy of Cornewall</hi> are in the Kings gift in the vacancy of a <hi>Duke of Cornewall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Receivers</hi> generall of the Kings Revenews, &amp;c. being about two and twenty in number, in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The ſurveior of the Greenewax, in the Kings gift; this Office was erected in the time of King <hi>James,</hi> upon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99762:24"/>of the Lord <hi>Treaſurer, Chancellor, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Treaſurer,</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the Kings learned Councell, as appeares by a Table ſet up in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſetting forth what the ſaid Officer is to doe in his place.</p>
               <p>The two <hi>Deputy Chamberlaines,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Joyners</hi> of the Tallies, in the two Chamberlaines gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Marſhall</hi> of the Court, now in the Kings gift.</p>
               <p>The two <hi>Parcell-markers</hi> being ſo called, becauſe they were ordained in the time of <hi>R.</hi> 2. to make the parcels of all Eſcheators accompts, and were wont to receive out of the Treaſurers Remembrancers Office, by a note un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands, all the Tranſcripts of Offices ſent thither yearly out of the Chancery, which were found by any Eſcheators; and out of thoſe they were to collect into a particular Roll, the parcels wherewith every Eſcheator was to be charged by the Auditor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his accompt; but the Eſcheators were in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> diſcharged from making accompts for any new Eſcheats, the ſame being put in charge in the Court of Wards, ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99762:24"/>as there is little or no uſe of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at this day, but for the old Eſcheats remaining in the Eſcheators accompts, whereof little or nothing is anſwered to the Crowne by them: howbeit they anciently made their accompts at large in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant at this day in the Pipe, and are ſtill called upon the Scroll of accomptants, and ought to ſtrike a Tally for their proffers every yeare, which of late time hath been neglected.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Clerk of the Nichils</hi> is in the Chancellors gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sealer</hi> of the Court is the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors gift.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chiefe Vſher of the Exchequer,</hi> is hee that by inheritance hath the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Exchequer Court,</hi> the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Chamber,</hi> and the houſe, with all the appurtenances, where the Court uſeth to dine when they ſit about the Kings buſineſſe; hee maketh proviſion for all the neceſſaries both of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and of the Receipt, and hath allowance thereof at every <hi>Liberate:</hi> and ſeeth to all places of the Court, that all Doores, Cheſts, Records and things be in ſafety from fire, water, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99762:25"/>other ſpoile, &amp;c. and hath the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of the reſt of the Vſhers, and the ſix ordinary Meſſengers of the Court, that they make a true delivery, to the <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> and all others of the Kings <hi>Proces,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The two <hi>Praiſers</hi> of the Court con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning uncuſtomed goods, in the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Treaſurers gift.</p>
               <p>The foure <hi>ordinary Vſhers</hi> of the Court, in the ſaid chiefe Vſhers gift.</p>
               <p>The ſix <hi>ordinary Meſſengers</hi> which carry the proces of the Court to She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, &amp;c. in the ſaid chiefe Vſhers gift.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the names of the ſaid Offices, in the ſaid <hi>Superior Exchequer,</hi> and in whoſe gift they are. But as to the particular duties which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to every of the ſaid offices, and to thoſe of the Receipt, or what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Records every of them hath in his cuſtody, and of what nature and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity they are, it is not my purpoſe to treat of in this place: for that would be a very great worke of it ſelfe; but onely of ſo much as ſhall fall in my way, concerning the managing and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Kings Revenues: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99762:25"/>thus much I may ſay, that there are ſo many excellent Records in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the two <hi>Remembrancers, Clerke of the Pipe,</hi> and in the ſeverall <hi>Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> both in the upper and lower <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</hi> As they may indeed bee called <hi>Treaſuries</hi> where thoſe Records are kept, they being the greateſt Treaſure of the Kingdome; inſomuch as I have heard a great Lawyer ſay, That he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver underſtood what Law was, till hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame up thoſe ſtaires. And to ſay the tuth, there muſt needs bee more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdinary matters, and great variety of taem found in that Court, whither all the other <hi>Courts</hi> of the Kingdome, as rivers to the ſea, in ſome kinde or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, have their reſort.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Offices</hi> in the inferior or lower <hi>Exchequer,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt,</hi> are theſe which follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>four Tellors of the Receipt</hi> (whoſe Offices are in the Kings gift) doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the Kings moneyes which are paid into the <hi>Receipt</hi> by <hi>Sheniffes, Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Farmers,</hi> and other <hi>Accomptants</hi> and <hi>Debtors</hi> whatſoever, and doe write a Bill thereof in parchment, expreſſing therein the ſumme by them received,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99762:26"/>and of whom, and for what; which Bill they deliver (not to the party that payeth the money,) but put it downe through a Trunke made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, into the Chamberlaines Court for a Tally to be ſtricken for diſcharge of the party.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Clerk of the Pell</hi> (whoſe Office is in the Lord Treaſurers gift) keepeth the Pell in parchment,
<note place="margin">Clerke of the Pell.</note> called <hi>Pellis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte,</hi> wherein every <hi>Tellers</hi> Bill with his name on it, is to be entred; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every ſuch Bill when it is entred, <hi>Recordatur</hi> to bee written in open Court, for a Controlment to charge the <hi>Teller</hi> with ſo much money as in the ſaid Bill is ſet downe.</p>
               <p>He alſe anciently kept another Pell, called <hi>Pellis Exitus,</hi> wherein every dayes iſſuing of any the moneyes paid into the <hi>Receipt,</hi> was to be entred, and by whom, and by what Warrant, privy Seale or Bill it was paid.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Auditor of the Receipt</hi> (whoſe Office is in the Lord Treaſurers gift) taketh up every Tellers parchment Bill,
<note place="margin">Auditor of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt.</note> after it is marked <hi>Recordatur</hi> by the <hi>Clerke of the Pell,</hi> and entred by the <hi>Controllers</hi> of the Pell, (who were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99762:26"/>alſo to make entry thereof in a <hi>Counter Pell</hi>) and fileth it upon a File; and then his Clerk that is called <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Talliar. &amp; Contratall.</hi> writeth double upon every <hi>Tally</hi> the whole let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Tellers Bill, that when the Tally is cloven both the foile and the ſtocke thereof, may have like letter u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Auditor doth alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all the ſaid parchment Bills in a Booke which is to him as <hi>Pellis Recepte;</hi> and by thoſe hee doth ſee what every <hi>Tellor</hi> receiveth weekly, and of whom, and maketh certificate thereof to the <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> &amp;c. as hee is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, how all the money of the Receipt particularly is paid and received: and to that end, maketh to every of the Tellors a <hi>Debentur,</hi> before any of them can pay any money out of the Receipt, be it upon Fees, privy Seales, or any Warrants whatſoever.</p>
               <p>He likewiſe keepeth the Lord <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers</hi> Key of the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> where the ancient <hi>Leagues</hi> of the Realme, the <hi>Perambulations</hi> of the <hi>Forreſts,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of <hi>Iuſticiar. Itiner.</hi> and divers other ancient Records of the <hi>Kings</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99762:27"/>Bench and Common Pleas doe lye both in the old <hi>Court of Wards,</hi> and in the old <hi>Parliament Houſe</hi> in the Cloiſter at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where no ſearch can be made without the ſaid key come with both the Chamberlains keyes thereof, where alſo the <hi>blacke Booke</hi> of the <hi>Recept, de neceſſariis Scacca. obſervanciis,</hi> agreeing in that point with the <hi>red Booke</hi> in the Kings Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers Office, is kept.</p>
               <p>The <hi>two Vnder-Chamberlaines</hi> bee both the Chamberlaines Deputies for the <hi>Recept,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Two Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines.</note> and their places in the ſaid <hi>Chamberlaines</hi> gift, the tallies ſo writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon (as before) are delivered to them, and the one of them holding the Tally, and the other the Cleaver and Mallet cleaveth the Tally in the midſt, and then one of them taking the ſtock and the other the foile, and the <hi>Clerke</hi> of the <hi>Pell,</hi> and his <hi>Controllers,</hi> their bookes, wherein the ſaid tellers Billes are recorded, the Cleaver ſaith, <hi>exam.</hi> and readeth the ſtocke aloud, and his fellow, the Clerke of the Pell, and his two controllers ſeeing the ſtocke to agree with them all, the ſaid ſtocke is delivered to the party that paid the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99762:27"/>money for his diſcharge, and the foile caſt into the Chamberlaines cheſt where they keep all their foiles toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their knives and the book of Doomeſday, &amp;c. untill the joyners fetch away the ſaid foiles which they keepe in their Office in the upper <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> to bee rejoyned and examined with the ſtocke delivered to the party for his diſcharge, which is not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of upon Record in the <hi>Pipe,</hi> by the firſt <hi>Secondary</hi> there, untill the ſame be ſo rejoyned and delivered in Court to the ſaid <hi>Secondary</hi> by the ſaid <hi>joyners</hi> with their marke teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by their examination the ſame agreeth with the <hi>foile</hi> in their cuſtody.</p>
               <p>And in the ſaid <hi>cheſt</hi> are alſo kept the <hi>keyes</hi> of the <hi>Treaſury</hi> under three locks, whereof the Auditor of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> hath one key belonging to the <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> the two <hi>under Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines</hi> another key, and the Vſher of the Receipt (whoſe place is in the Kings gift) another, who attendeth by himſelfe or his Deputy, and is to doe all things there which other Vſhers ought to doe and to keep the Receipt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99762:28"/>as the Vſher by Inheritance doth the upper <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>under Chamberlaines</hi> make all ſearches in the Treaſury for any Records, at the ſuit of the parties, and copies and exemplifications of the ſame, whereof the Fees are divided betweene them and the keeper of the Lord Treaſurers key.</p>
               <p>The <hi>cutter of the Tallies</hi> is another Officer in the Receipt:
<note place="margin">The cutter of the Tallies.</note> of the Lord Treaſurers guift, who provideth ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and proportionable haſells and cutteth them to fit lengths into foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare ſides, to the end they may the better be cloven and written upon, and caſteth them into the Court from time to time as any of them be called for, and receiveth his dividend Fee (with the <hi>Clerke of the Pell,</hi> the <hi>ſcriptor talliar.</hi> and <hi>Vnder Chamberlaines</hi>) of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ſueth it out.</p>
               <p>The <hi>foure ordinary Meſſengers</hi> of the Receipt,
<note place="margin">The foure ordinary meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt.</note> (whoſe places are now in the Kings gift) are Purſuyvants attending upon the Lord Treaſurer for carrying his letters and precepts to all the <hi>Cuſtomers, Controllers</hi> and <hi>Shearchers</hi> throughout the land, who are to ride
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99762:28"/>and goe upon any other his Majeſties Meſſages, where it is his Lordſhips pleaſure to command them.</p>
               <p>Thus much in briefe concerning the <hi>Inferior Court of the Exchequer,</hi> called the <hi>Receipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been the more large in ſetting downe the particular grounds and Rules of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> according to the common Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, and the ancient courſe of the ſaid Court for the charging, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, bringing in and anſwering of the Revenues of the Crowne, both cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and caſuall: and that eſpecially for theſe reaſons following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the wiſedome and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our Anceſtors may appeare in providing for the indempnity of the King and his Subjects; wherein, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, care is to bee taken, that (as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to bee charged) ſo nothing to bee diſcharged but by matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that no one Officer is truſted alone with the bringing in, charging, diſcharging, receiving, or iſſuing out of the Kings Revenues, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as for the better and more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99762:29"/>controlment and ſecurity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all the ſaid Revenues both certaine and caſuall, are to bee reduced from their originall fountaines and heads, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>Great Roll</hi> of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stat. de Rutland. Anno 10. E. 1.</note> being the old <hi>Channell</hi> or <hi>Pipe</hi> for conveying the ſame into the Kings <hi>Receipt.</hi> And from the ſaid <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>Great Roll</hi> (not onely for the reaſons formerly alledged, but for controlment ſake) proces is firſt to be written to the Sheriffes by the <hi>Controller</hi> of <hi>the Pipe,</hi> who yearly writes a duplicate of the ſaid Annuall or great Roll, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter controlment thereof. And that this is, and ought to bee ſo, the conſtant courſe now obſerved and continued in the Offices of the <hi>two Remembrancers of the Exchequer,</hi> will make it unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable: for that neither from the <hi>originals of the Chancery,</hi> nor for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther debts or ſummes of money recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the King in either of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, any proces is made to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes by either of them, for leavying thereof, but the ſame are at this day, (as formerly hath been uſed) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt drawne downe from thence, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the ſaid <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>great Roll,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99762:29"/>according to the ancient courſe of the ſaid Court, and the ſaid ſtatute of Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>Anno</hi> 10. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. And the like courſe hath been alwayes uſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved concerning the Accompts of <hi>Collectors, Cuſtomers, Receivers</hi> of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Temporalties,</hi> and all other <hi>Accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> whatſoever, within the ſurvey of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> For though they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the <hi>Auditors</hi> before the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, Chancellour</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> or all or ſome of them; and entred in the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of both the Remembrancers, yet they are not thereby fully determined, before they come to the Pipe, where they are to remaine upon Record for ever, as the Kings and Subjects evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and where their <hi>Tallies</hi> being firſt examined, and joyned with their Foyles, are to bee allowed, and the <hi>Debts</hi> and <hi>Supers</hi> therein depending (if any ſuch bee) entred in the ſaid <hi>great Roll,</hi> ſo as proces may be written from thence for levying thereof, as before is obſerved.</p>
               <p>And as there is no one Officer in the <hi>Superior Exchequer</hi> ſolely truſted, ſo it is moſt evident, that in the <hi>inferior Court</hi> there is to bee a concurrence of many
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99762:30"/>Officers in the truſt: for the <hi>Tellors</hi> Bill is not delivered to the party which payes the money, nor truſted with any one Officer to charge the ſaid <hi>Tellor</hi> therewith; but it is entred with the <hi>Clerke of the Pell,</hi> and with the <hi>Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Pell,</hi> and againe entred with the <hi>Auditor</hi> of the <hi>Receipt,</hi> who files the ſame: and the ſtocke of the Tally delivered to the party for his diſcharge; and yet this to be no diſcharge for him, till it be rejoyned with the other part, and allowed in the great Roll. All which caution (without doubt) hath been by the great wiſedome and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of our Anceſtors, found neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be impoſed and obſerved for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of the frauds and abuſes which otherwiſe would enſue to the Crown; many falſities having been anciently diſcovered in Tallies for want of joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as <hi>Hill. Record. Anno</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>Rot.</hi> 10. <hi>ex parte Rem. Theſ. cum multos aliis,</hi> and both in the time of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory: Many ſuch falſities having been diſcovered in Tallies for want of joyning; ſo as I may conclude this point with <hi>Gervaſius Tilburienſis,</hi> That
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99762:30"/>no Officer is ſolely truſted with the Kings Revenues, no not the Treaſurer himſelfe: And the reaſon which hee gives for it, is, that beſides the control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great <hi>Roll</hi> (being the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers Roll) by the Chancellors Roll, there was a third Roll to bee ordained, <hi>Quia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>triplex funis difficile ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51-118" type="pages">
               <p>And thirdly and laſtly, that it may appeare that the Sheriffes onely were the conſtant Officers and Miniſters for leavying and bringing in the certaine Revenues and Debts of the Crowne. And that the ordinary proces of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to Sheriffes for leavying and bringing in therof, was and is moſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and efficatious (as to the King) and moſt ſecure and ſafe (as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) in caſe they ſhall conceale any thing upon their accompts which they ſhall ſo receive, as hath been formerly obſerved. And that there will bee no need of Reſort to bee made for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of <hi>Meſſengers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall.</note> or to make uſe of any ſuch <hi>Arbitrary</hi> or <hi>Illegall</hi> courſes ſo burdenſome to his Majeſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for bringing in any part thereof, if the ſame be written out to Sheriffes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99762:31"/>in due time, and the Sheriffes ſtrictly holden to the anſwering there of, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſting and ſetting off <hi>de Anno in Annum,</hi> his Majeſties good debts, and Farmes, but by juſt matter of Record, according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme.</p>
               <p>And if the uſe of <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> or any other arbitrary courſe were allowable, it is probable that the nupriall Queens of this Realme, participating ſo much of the Regality of the Crowne, having a <hi>Court,</hi> a <hi>Chancellor</hi> and <hi>Seale</hi> of their owne, might make ſome uſe thereof for bringing in the Arrerages of Rents, their <hi>Aurum Reginae,</hi> and other debts and duties belonging to them in their owne particular eſtates; but it is ſo far otherwiſe, that by the common Lawes of this Land, they have the ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for bringing in their ſaid debts and duties as the King hath, as appeares by a Writ directed to the Sheriffe of <hi>Norfolke</hi> and <hi>Suffolke,</hi> out of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> 24. <hi>Maii, Anno</hi> 14. <hi>Edwardi primi.</hi> The tenor of which Writ fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99762:31"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="writ">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>Edwardus Dei gratia Angliae Rex, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Hiberniae, &amp; Dux Aquitan. </signed>
                        <salute>Vic. Norff. &amp; Suff. ſalutem, </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Cum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum antiquam conſuetudinem approbatam, &amp; hactenus optentam, Idem modus in debitis Reginarum levandis &amp; redden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, qui &amp; in noſtris ſervari debeat, ac debita noſtra juxta candem conſuetudinem a aebitor. noſtris ſunt levanda &amp; nobis reddenda antequam quibuſcunque Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor corundem de debitis ſuis ſatisſiat, Cum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Willielmus de Huntingfield cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſime matri noſtre Alionore Reginae An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glie in xxxij. l'. teneatur prout nobis conſtat per inſpect. Rotulorum de Scaceario noſtro, I dem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Wilielmus teneatur quam plur. in diverſis pecuniarum ſummis prout tu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornaſti coram Baron. in craſtino clauſi Paſche prox. pretcrit. volentes ipſam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem noſtram prerogativa predict. quoad debita ſua levand. ſicut aliae Reginae An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae eadem in caſu conſil. ſint gaviſe, tibi precipimus quod de bonis &amp; catall. &amp; de exit terrar. ipſius Willielmi in Balliva tua fieri facias predictas xxxij. l'. antequam debita quorundam creditorum ſuorum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur. Ita quod eas habeas ad idem Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carium noſtrum apud Weſtmonaſterium à die ſanctae Trinitate in xv. dies Waltero de
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99762:32"/>Caſtello cuſtodi Auri ejuſdem liberand. &amp; hoc breve Teſte, &amp;c.</p>
                     <bibl>Per Rotul. memor. de anno 54. H. 3.</bibl>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And that this courſe by Writs dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to Sheriffes, and no other, was uſed as well in thoſe ancient times as in all the times ſithence, even unto, and in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. for bringing in the debts and duties belonging to the nuptiall Queenes of England, appeares by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers like Writs and Records remaining in the <hi>Exchequer:</hi> And the reaſon why ſuch a legall courſe and no other was allowed to the ſaid Queens, for getting in their debts, I conceive was this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Subject might demurre or take Iſſue upon any ſuch writ where there was juſt cauſe, which he could not doe in caſe a meſſenger or other demand out of the <hi>Queens</hi> Court had beene made for the ſame.</p>
               <p>I have the rather vouched this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent here concerning the manner of levying the <hi>Queens</hi> debts, in regard ſome of the Auditors of the Revenue having of late moved and preſſed the Lords Commiſſioners of the Treaſury at
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99762:32"/>the Councell board for ſigning of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to meſſengers for bringing in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>ſupers</hi> and debts aſwell within the Queenes joynture as parcell of the Kings Revenues, depending in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of generall Receivors, which a noble Lord at that board (being tender of all unjuſt vexations to his Majeſties Subjects) withſtanding, as conceiving the ordinary proces of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to be moſt proper and ſufficient for bringing in his Majeſties debts, a dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was made to the Barons of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to call unto them the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ſaid Court and to certifie whether the imployment of meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in thoſe caſes were legall, who certified their Lordſhips that their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in that kinde was not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law; and that by the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the Laws of this Kingdome, the Auditors ought to deliver the Accompts of the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors and miniſters of the Revenew in charge before them into the Pipe every yeare by the twentieth of March, ſo as proces might bee made from thence to the Sheriffes for levying of the <hi>ſupers</hi> and debts depending in thoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99762:33"/>Accompts; but I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake ſomewhat more of this in the enſuing diſcourſe concerning the great and ſuperfluous charge and loſſe the Crowne hath beene put unto in bringing in thoſe Revenewes, which was alwayes carefully avoided by the like wiſdome of our Anceſtors, it being provided by the foreſaid Statute of the <hi>Exchequer Anno</hi> 51. <hi>H.</hi> 3. that the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> be not charged with mo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then is neceſſary. For as our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had one principall care in the conſtitution of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to ſee that the Kings Farmes, Rents and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſperate debts, and duties were duely anſwered and not prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or poſted off from yeare to yeare, whereby they might either grow deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate,
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing of the Kings good debts makes them deſperate or grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note> or become grievances to the ſubject by being charged upon the <hi>debtors ſuerties</hi> or the <hi>purchaſers</hi> of their lands as hath beene formerly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſo had they a like ſpeciall care to ſee that all unneceſſary and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous charge in bringing the ſaid Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes into the Kings Coffers ſhould be avoided, which rules if they had beene of late yeares obſerved in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99762:33"/>
                  <hi>Exchequer</hi> many great and unſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loſſes to the Crowne, and many unſufferable grievances to the Subject might have been prevented.</p>
               <p>It is true that for ſome private ends, and other reſpects upon the great glut of Revenew which came to the Crowne in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. many <hi>new Exchequers</hi> and <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new</hi> were created and erected by <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> (beſides the Court of the <hi>Dutchy of Lancaſter</hi> erected in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.) As the Court of <hi>Angmentations,</hi> the Court of generall <hi>Surveiors,</hi> the Court of firſt <hi>Fruits and Tenths,</hi> the Court of <hi>Wards &amp; Liveries.</hi> But it is well known what is become of moſt of thoſe Courts, as namely the Court of <hi>Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, Generall Surveiors,</hi> and <hi>firſt Fruits and Tenths,</hi> all of them being diſſolved by Act of Parliament in <hi>anno primo Mariae Regine,</hi> and turned into the old Channell, <hi>viz.</hi> annexed to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> where (be the Kings Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new two millions or more) it may be as well managed and brought in, as if it were but one; the reaſons why the ſaid Courts were then ſo diſſolved being in thoſe dayes notoriouſly knowne and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99762:34"/>openly declared, as namely, for that the <hi>Revenewes</hi> in thoſe <hi>Courts,</hi> were in a manner wholly waſted and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the new and unneceſſary <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> of thoſe Courts; the Court of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and that of the <hi>Wards and Liveries,</hi> being alſo offered by the <hi>Parliament</hi> at the ſame time to be by the ſaid <hi>Queen Mary</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner diſſolved by her letters patents and annexed to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> where all the benefit ariſing by <hi>Wardſhips and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries</hi> was before the erection of the ſaid Court, <hi>Anno</hi> 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. anſwered to the Crowne.</p>
               <p>And howſoever the ſaid Court of Wards and Liveries (as being at that time a profitable Court to the Crown) might in the ſame time of <hi>Queen Mary</hi> eſcape from being reannexed to the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> nevertheleſſe it is not a little ſtrange that the ſaid <hi>Dutchy Court of Lancaſter</hi> ſhould both then and ever ſince be continued by it ſelf, at ſo great a charge for ſo ſmall a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew, it having coſt the Crowne ſince the ſaid firſt yeare of <hi>Queen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> neare upon two <hi>hundred thouſand pounds,</hi> which might have been ſaved
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99762:34"/>if the ſame had been then annexed to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and there managed in ſuch manner and ſort as was then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may ſeeme more ſtrange when it ſhall be made to appeare that the generall and particular <hi>Receivers, Bayliffes</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> of the <hi>Court of Augmentations,</hi> which by the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Parliament Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Mariae</hi> (when the ſaid Court was annexed to the <hi>Exchequer</hi>) were intended to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged and put to their pentions, and the ſaid Revenew to be from that time brought in and anſwered by the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes</hi> of each County according to the ancient courſe, have beene ever ſince continued in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable burthen and charge to the Crown, and infinite grievance of the Subject, it having coſt the Crowne ſince the diſſolution of the ſaid Court <hi>Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Mariae</hi> (for the private ends and reſpects of ſome few) not ſo little as <hi>ſix hundred thouſand pounds,</hi> which might have been ſaved if the <hi>Revenews</hi> of that Court had been managed in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> according to the ſaid anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent courſe, and in ſuch ſort as was then
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99762:35"/>intended by the ſaid <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides all this to make good the old <hi>maxime, Vno inconvenienti conceſſo mille ſequuntur,</hi> it will appeare that in all this time there hath beene no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of controlement of the <hi>Accompts</hi> of the ſaid <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>particular Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, Bayliffes</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Revenews</hi> amounting to 100000 pounds <hi>per aunum</hi> and upwards, as namely, the <hi>Receivors</hi> have not beene ſworne to their Accompts yearly, their tallies not joyned, their accompts not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with the <hi>two Remembrancers,</hi> nor delivered into the <hi>Pipe</hi> as by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Article <hi>Anno</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Inter Hil Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. an. 1 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riae ex parte Rem. Theſſ. Articulo 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Mariae</hi> upon the annexation of the ſaid Court of <hi>Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations</hi> to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be yearly performed by the twentieth of March, and ſo lately cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the Barous of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> as is formerly alledged; the ſaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts having been ever ſince left to the determination and keeping of the ſait <hi>Auditors</hi> in their particular aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without any maner of controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by meanes whereof there may be many great concealements in the ſaid accompts which none of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99762:35"/>Kings Officers in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> can diſcover, but the <hi>Auditor</hi> himſelfe.</p>
               <p>And for the grievances which have been by the ſame meanes occaſioned to his Majeſties Subjects by reaſon of the multitude of <hi>Supers</hi> and <hi>Arrerages</hi> of <hi>Rents,</hi> which from time to time ever ſince have depended in thoſe <hi>Accompts</hi> upon the <hi>Farmers, Bayliffes</hi> and <hi>Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Revenewes.</hi> And upon the <hi>Receivors</hi> themſelves, ſome for 5000 l'. ſome 10000 l'. ſome more, ſome leſſe, both in the time of the late <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and the late <hi>King Iames:</hi> The infinite numbers of eſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſeiſures of the lands of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivors and their ſureties, and of the lands which came from the ſaid Debtors by purchaſe or diſcent, and orders of Court concerning the ſame in the time of the ſaid <hi>K. Iames</hi> before the Stat. of 21 <hi>Iac.</hi> for diſcharging of old debts in his now Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> time, together with the loud outeries againſt <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> lately imployed at the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome patentees for old debts, for bringing in the like <hi>arrerages</hi> of <hi>Rents</hi> behind, which depended in ſome of thoſe accounts, ſome for 10, ſome 20,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99762:36"/>ſome thirty yeare before they were ſent in proces, will ſufficiently teſtifie.</p>
               <p>And as if the continuation of the foreſaid <hi>Receivers,</hi> and other needleſſe and unprofitable <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptants,</hi> had not beene burdenſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to the Crowne, there have been of late introduced &amp; added <hi>two new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers,</hi> and two <hi>new Auditors</hi> for the <hi>Revenue</hi> of <hi>Recuſants,</hi> with ſundry dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions procured for transferring the charge of the ſaid <hi>Revenues</hi> from the <hi>great Roll</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to the ſaid new <hi>Auditors,</hi> and for ſuperſeding of all <hi>proces</hi> to <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> other then for ſuch debts owing by <hi>Recuſants,</hi> as their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers cannot levie; as alſo for the payment of ſo much thereof, as the ſaid <hi>Sheriffes</hi> ſhould leavie to the hands of the ſaid new <hi>Receivers</hi> reſpectively, which was formerly uſed to be paid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings Receipt. How farre this bold attempt, together with the <hi>Non-obſtantes</hi> in the Leaſes of Recuſants lands, might have trenched as well to the ſubverſion of the good lawes made againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> as to the diverſion and conſumption of the ſaid Revenue, (if this Parliament had not been ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99762:36"/>called by his Majeſty) may wel be imagined.</p>
               <p>And if the removing and altering of the ancient bounds betweene neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and neighbour bee forbidden by the Law of God as a great offence and a curſed thing, by reaſon of the great trouble and unquietneſſe which is cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereby, how much more do they offend which remove and alter the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient bounds which our forefathers have ſet betweene the King and his people, either in the conſtitution of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or in the <hi>execution</hi> of the Lawes and Statutes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome appointed and limited for the government and ordering of the Kings Revenews there? In which caſe it were to bee wiſhed that ſome ſevere Law might be made for the puniſhment of thoſe which under any ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever goe about to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure any warrant for the altering or removing any the bounds formerly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited or ordained for the anſwering and bringing in of the ſaid Revenews, unleſſe it be by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great miſchiefes and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences both to the King and Subject enſue thereby.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99762:37"/>
               <p>And if it be true that <hi>Sheriffes</hi> have been (time beyond memory of man) the <hi>Receivors</hi> of all the certaine rents and debts whatſoever belonging to the Crown within the limits of their <hi>Baily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks</hi>) other then ſuch as are to be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately paid into his Majeſties Receipt of <hi>Excheq.</hi> or into his <hi>Chamber, Wardrob,</hi> to the <hi>cofferer</hi> of his <hi>houſhold,</hi> or the like, how abſurd a thing is it for the <hi>Sheriffe,</hi> having received ſuch rents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r debts from the Kings <hi>Tenants</hi> or <hi>debtors</hi> to pay the ſame over to one of the Kings <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors,</hi> for him to pay into the Kings <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt,</hi> and not to pay the ſame immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately into the Kings Receipt with the other moneies due upon his Accompt, or why the <hi>Farmer</hi> or <hi>Collector</hi> being to pay his rent or charge into the Kings Receipt ſhould not rather pay the ſame to the Sheriffe then to a Receivor who muſt be paid for portage beſides other allowances from the King. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which ſuppoſition I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it would ſeeme a ſtrange peece of husbandry to the Crowne, if the Collectors or Farmers of the <hi>great Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> of the <hi>Subſidies</hi> in every County (who are to pay their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99762:37"/>moneyes into the <hi>Receipt</hi>) ſhould bee appointed to pay the ſame to ſome of the Receivors, and the ſame Receivors to pay it into the Kings <hi>Receipt;</hi> ſuch kind of husbandry as this, is the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of other <hi>Receivors</hi> beſides the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes</hi> for receiving the certaine Rents and Debts of the Crowne at this day.</p>
               <p>And for proofe that the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> have alwaies beene the <hi>Receivors</hi> of the certaine Rents and Debts belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Crowne, and other <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> avoided as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and needleſſe, I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon any other proofe for this, then what I have herein for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſet downe, to make it unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but that one <hi>Writ</hi> of 16. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. directed from the King to the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the then <hi>Exchequer,</hi> which in effect was ſeconded by an <hi>Act of Councell</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="writ">
                  <body>
                     <head>The tenor of the ſaid Writ <hi>anno</hi> 16. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>Henricus Dei gratia Rex, &amp;c. </signed>
                        <salute>Theſſ. &amp; Baron. de Scaccar. ſalutem. </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Cum mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99762:38"/>ſit nobis qualiter dilectus noſter Robertus Whittingham Chivaler hab. of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium Receptoris generalis omnium terr. &amp;c. que fuerunt Iohannis nuper Ducis Bedford. Avunc. noſtri cariſſimi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct. &amp; quod officium predict. non eſt ad commodum noſtrum, quia vadia &amp; feoda quae ea de cauſa de nobis percepta ſunt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt bene fore omiſſa. Et quod Vicecomites noſtri poſſunt bene levare Revenciones in manibus noſtris exiſten. prout fuit ante hoc tempus. Ideo vobis mandamus quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Robertum exoneretis ab officio pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto &amp;c.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>By which it appeares that this one extraordinary <hi>Receivor</hi> in the time of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. was deemed a burthen and unneceſſary charge to the Crown, and therefore according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> thought fit to be diſcharged of his Receipts, and the ſame to be transferred to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, <hi>prout fuit ante hoc tempus,</hi> which was ſo done accordingly.</p>
               <p>The like we ſhall finde in the third and fourth yeare of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> in a report made to their Majeſties by the then Lords of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99762:38"/>Councell, upon ſome queſtion (after the annexation of the Court of aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations to the <hi>Exchequer</hi>) whether the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> or <hi>Receivors</hi> were the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Miniſters for receiving the Rents and Revenues of the Crowne; and whether the Dutchy Court of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ought not to be annexed to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> and all Manors to bee demiſed in groſſe with their caſualties at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Rent, for cutting off all ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of expenſes.</p>
               <p>The Report is as followeth.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <p>SVmus in priori opinione, quod Viceco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſit maxime idoneus qui recipiat annuos redditus veſtrarum Majeſtatum infra limites ſuorum officiorum, &amp; de illis reſpondeat veſtris Majeſtatibus.</p>
                  <p>Et ad id quod dicitur Vicecomites male jam reſpondere de iis quae corum fidei com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittuntur putemus id eo fieri, vel quiae officiarii Scaccarii non urgeant neque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent prout corum officii eſt, vel quia ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio male eliguntur: Et utri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> huic mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> facillime ſuccurritur ſi Vicecomites bene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligantur.</p>
                  <p>Et quod Vicecomites ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt ad hanc rem
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99762:39"/>maxime idonei, movemur iis rationibus quae ſequuntur.</p>
                  <p>Vetera exempla hujus regni cum optime &amp; cum maximo honore regeretur oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt quod omnes annui redditus coram ſolvebantur per Vicecomites.</p>
                  <p>Nec putamus quod Vicecomites (preſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſi bene eligantur) erunt tam tardi in pecuniis ſolvendis computíſve reddendis, quam Receptores &amp; ſunt &amp; ſemper hacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus fuerunt.</p>
                  <p>Vicecomites (quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> officium annuum eſt) &amp; annuatim computa reddunt, non poſſunt celare pecunias veſtrarum Majeſtatum quemadmodum Receptores ſolent.</p>
                  <p>Receptores enim (quorum officium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum eſt) debita prioris anni ſolvunt ex redditibus ſequentis, quae fraus vitabitur ſi Vicecomites perficiantur huic Cure: ac etiam annue expenſe quae nunc fiunt pro multis officiariis ceſſabunt.</p>
                  <p>Vicecomites eliguntur de honeſtioribus, Equitibus, ſive Generoſis ſingulorum Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum: Receptores ſunt plerun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> homines nullius eſtimationis.</p>
                  <p>Vicecomites Eliguntur annuatim per ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras Majeſtates ex conſenſu Magnatum &amp; Judicum Regni: Receptores autem aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>untur per privatos favores amicorum.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99762:39"/>
                  <p>Sumus etiam in priori opinione quod terrae &amp; poſſeſſiones Ducatus Lancaſtriae, poſſunt bene reduci ad Scaccarium: Et quod fieri poteſt ſalvis etiam omnibus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonis ſive tenentibus dict. Ducatus, ſuis libertatibus, privilegiis &amp; conſuetudini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quibus omnibus frui &amp; gaudere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, Coloni &amp; Tenentes praedicti, non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus integre in Scaccario, quam nunc fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur in Curia Ducatus, &amp; ad hanc o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionem movemur iis rationibus.</p>
                  <p>Annue expenſe quae fiunt pro multis Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiariis Ducatus ceſſabunt.</p>
                  <p>Terrae &amp; poſſeſſiones Ducatus Lancae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriae, cum ſint in multis &amp; ſeperatis Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus poſſunt carum poſſeſſionum annui redditus per Com. illorum Vicecomites uno labore colligi ſimul cum aliis redditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</p>
                  <p>Cum Ducatus Lancaſtriae jam deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit ad Reginam unacum Corona, non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus quare non debeant ejuſdem Duca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus terrae &amp; poſſeſſion. gubernari in Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cario quemaedmodum poſſeſſiones Principat. Walliae, Ducatus Cornub. Eboraci, &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſilium.</p>
                  <p>Nobis etiaem non videtur praejudiciale ſed vaelde utile veſtris Majeſtatibus quod Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neria &amp; cum illis omnia caſualia locentur
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99762:40"/>ad firmam, reſervatis Boſcis, Wardis, maritagiis, Miner. &amp; Advocationibus Eccleſiarum.</p>
                  <p>Idem quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> putamus de ſylvis ceduis quos ſubboſcos diximus, quos utile puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ad firmam dimittere &amp; movemur ad hanc opinionem iis rationibus.</p>
                  <p>Si locentur Maneria atque omnium a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum generum terrae &amp; poſſeſſiones cum caſualibus &amp; ſubboſcis annui. redditus veſtrarum Majeſtatum erunt certi qui nunc incerti ſunt.</p>
                  <p>Annui ſumptus reparationem Seneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callorum corum qui Nemora cuſtodiunt, &amp; multorum aliorum officiar. ceſſabunt.</p>
                  <p>Multi annui redditus, &amp; multa ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, quae nunc partim, dolo malo, partim, negligentia Seneſcallorum Balliorum &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum officiar. non exiguntur &amp; ita paulatim pereunt: ſemper ſolventur cum firmarii &amp; propter privatum lucrum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; propter obligationem qua tenebun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur diligentius illa curabunt.</p>
                  <p>Miſeri Coloni, ſive pauperiores tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes quibus variis artibus extorquentur pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniae tam per officiarios quam per eor um famulos, honeſtius tractabuntur ſi dicta Maneria cum caſualibus &amp; ſylve cedue dentur ad Firmam honeſtis viris.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99762:40"/>
                  <p>Lucra etiam illa quae ex caſualibus &amp; ſubboſcis proveniunt, &amp; nunc malis arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extorquentur per Officiarios, venient directe ad uſum veſtrarum Majeſtatum, atque id ſine ullo praejudicio pauperiorum Colonorum qui plus favoris ſemper inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient in vicino firmario honeſto quam in extraneis emptoribus, Baliis, vel ſilvarum cuſtodibus.</p>
                  <p>Et preterea poteſt aliis modis ſatis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videri contra firmariorum avaritiam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Officiariorum vero infinitas fraudes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter provideri non poteſt, idque long a expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientia nimis cognitum eſt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>As by the ſaid Report remaining in his Majeſties Library at White-Hall, (amongſt other things) may appeare.</p>
               <p>Wherein it is moſt evident of what uſe and eſtimation Sheriffes (being but for a year) have alwayes been, for bringing in the Revenues of the Crowne; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they bee well choſen, and held to the performance of their duties by the Officers of <hi>Exchequer:</hi> with this further obſervation, How remiſſe the Receivors were in thoſe dayes, and had ever been in paying what they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and making their accompts in due
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99762:41"/>time. Beſides, it is well knowne how many Receivors both in the time of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the late King <hi>James,</hi> as is before obſerved, have broken for very great ſummes of money, which were never paid at ſuch a rate <hi>per annum,</hi> as the intereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted unto: But it cannot be proved that ever any one Sheriffe broke in that kinde.</p>
               <p>Moreover, by the ſaid Report may be obſerved the faithfull advice given to the Queene, by the ſaid Lords of her Councell, to demiſe all her Manors in Groſſe with the <hi>Caſualties</hi> and <hi>Woods,</hi> and ſo to make her Rents certaine, and cut off the great charge of Stewards, Bailiffes, and other Officers: for that otherwiſe, <hi>Contra Officiarum infinitas fraudes provideri non poteſt idque longa experientia nimis cognitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> as before is obſerved. On the other ſide, it may bee obſerved, whether the advice of thoſe Officers who then adviſed the Queen to keep the <hi>Royalties</hi> and <hi>Caſualties</hi> of her Manors in her own hands by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Stewards and Bailiffes of her own to manage the ſame, and onely to demiſe the <hi>Demeanes</hi> of every Manor at
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99762:41"/>the old Rent payably halfe yearly, was the beſt Counſell; we that have had the experience of thoſe and our owne times, can beſt judge, as thoſe Lords in their experience then found it, <hi>viz.</hi> that it had been much better for the Queen to have demiſed the Mannors in groſſe with the caſualties (as was by them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed) at a certaine Rent; For that upon ſeverall <hi>mediums</hi> caſt up by the <hi>Auditors</hi> of the profits of <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Caſualties,</hi> and of the Fees of <hi>Bayliffes,</hi> and the Fees and Diets of <hi>Stewards</hi> for keeping of Courts, it hath appeared that the Fees and Dyets, of the ſaid <hi>Stewards</hi> and <hi>Bayliffes</hi> have in all times ſithence exceeded the caſualties three thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> at leaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Fees</hi> of the <hi>Receivors, Collectors</hi> and <hi>Auditors (cauſa exercitii)</hi> and the <hi>riding charges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for that it alſo appeareth that the beſt and moſt valuable and choiſeſt parts of every Mannor have been demiſed at the old Rent for three lives and for xxj. xxxj. and xl. years in reverſion, booke after booke, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Crowne hath beene by that meanes in a manner foreſtalled
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99762:42"/>from making any benefit thereof, as if the ſame had beene granted in Fee Farme. So as I ſhall be bold for the reaſons aforeſaid to conclude that the ancient courſe of demiſing the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Lands intirely with the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties by the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> for the time being by way of <hi>Cuſtody</hi> with the ordinary <hi>proviſo</hi> of <hi>ſi quis plus dare volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orit de increme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſine fraude vel malo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Kings lands in <hi>Cuſtody</hi> by the Lord Treaſurer with the proviſo of <hi>Si quis da re voluerit &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> reſerving the beſt Rent with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exceptions before mentioned, was and is the moſt prudent and ſafeſt courſe for the Crowne; for that then upon all occaſions, either for proviſion for the royall Iſſue, or other urgent occaſions, the King might have his lands at his owne diſpoſall when he pleaſed.</p>
               <p>But now at the cloſe and upſhot of all,
<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Sheriffes of their exceſſive charge &amp; trouble in paſſing their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts.</note> the caſe being cleared that the <hi>Sheriffe</hi> is the onely <hi>Officer</hi> appointed by the Lawes of this Kingdome for bringing in and anſwering the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Crowne, I cannot ſtoppe mine eares againſt the loud cries which <hi>Sheriffes</hi> make of the great and exceſſive <hi>charge</hi> and trouble which they are unjuſtly put unto in paſſing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99762:42"/>their <hi>Accompts</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By reaſon they have beene infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Officers of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to take into their charge all the ſeiſures upon their forraine Accompts (leavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or not leaviable) and other dead <hi>Farmes</hi> and <hi>deſperate debts</hi> which they cannot leavy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To pay divers new exacted and extorted Fees and Rewards upon the paſſing of their Accompts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To collect and leavy at their own charge the <hi>Greenwax</hi> moneyes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Majeſties caſual Revenues and Debts, granted in Farme, and given to divers Farmers and other Patentees who take the benefit thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To accompt before the <hi>parcell maker</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> for ſuch <hi>fellons</hi> goods and other like <hi>Eſcheates</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they have beene and are charged by the <hi>Auditors</hi> upon their <hi>forraine Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts,</hi> when there were or are any ſuch.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And for that alſo divers <hi>Hundreds, Wapontakes</hi> and <hi>Gaols,</hi> parcell of their <hi>Balywicks,</hi> which by ſeverall Acts of Parliament have been annexed to their Counties, have beene contrary to the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99762:43"/>ſaid Statutes granted away to ſundry perſons, and ſevered from their ſaid Counties, ſo as they cannot have the Bayliffes at their command, and yet are ſtill charged upon their Accompts with their ſaid Bailywicks under the title <hi>de proficuis Com.</hi> By reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all men of quality have beene of late much diſcouraged to take the ſaid Office upon them.</p>
               <p>Which ſaid complaints of theirs (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo juſt and true) may not be paſſed over in ſilence, but ſome fit remedies applied for their better incouragement according to the Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the ſaid Office of Sheriffe being an Office of high truſt and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both for the ſervice of the King and Common-wealth;
<note place="margin">The ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius &amp; cu ſtos Cem.</hi>
                  </note> and the Sheriff being anciently ſtiled <hi>Firmarius &amp; cuſtos Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt, as to the injury offered to Sheriffes, in charging them with all the ſeiſures in their forraine Accompts, and with other dead Farmes and deſperate debts which at their appoſalls they averre to be illeviable; all Sheriffes ought to be relieved herein by the foreſaid Statute of <hi>Rutland An.</hi> 10. <hi>E.</hi> 1. which provides that nothing ſhall bee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99762:43"/>written out to Sheriffes but ſuch debts whereof there is ſome hope that ſomething may bee leavied, and that all dead Farms and deſperate debts, are to be removed from the <hi>Annual</hi> into the <hi>exannuall Roll,</hi> and not to be written out in proces to Sheriffes, but only read to them at their Appoſalls to ſee if any thing may bee revived: And that a Commiſſion bee awarded out of the Treaſurers Remembrancers Office to faithfull and circumſpect men in every County (as is before preſcribed) to inquire of the ſeverall ſeiſures char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon Sheriffes in their forraine Accompts which they cannot leavy, to ſee if the ſame can be revived and made good; and if upon returne of the ſaid Commiſſion any of the ſaid ſeiſures ſhall prove defective and illeviable, that then the ſaid ſeiſures to be removed and diſcharged out of the ſaid forraine Accompt, and put into an <hi>exannuall Roll</hi> as aforeſaid, and the Sheriffe to be charged no more there with untill the ſame ſhall be revived: And for the time to come Sheriffes to bee charged with no more then is written forth in proces to them, nor with any <hi>Debt,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99762:44"/>Farme</hi> or <hi>ſumme of money</hi> which at their <hi>Appoſals</hi> they ſhall averre to be illevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: they being many wayes puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Lawes formerly alledged if they ſhall violate their oathes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p n="2 and 3">2. 3. And as to the wrong which She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes have undergone by paying new exacted and extorted Fees, It is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of every honeſt man that thoſe beaſts of prey which have ſo unconſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably taken thoſe new exacted Fees (who are in truth a great ſcandall to the whole Court and State) may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed or quite hunted out of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer;</hi> they will eaſily be found out, ſome of their abuſes to wards the King, and extortions towards the Subject appearing upon Record; and other of them having ſurreptitiouſly procured a kinde of new Authority to exact what Fees they pleaſe of Sheriffes and <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Liberties</hi> under colour of an Accompt to be made to the King for a ſuppoſed nothing.</p>
               <p>And that there may be a table in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> wherein the ancient due Fees of all the Offices of the ſaid Court may be regulated and moderated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99762:44"/>to the quality and quantity of all manner of buſineſſes, with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to what was taken in the time of the late Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> &amp; ſome penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be inflicted by a Bill to be paſſed in Parliament upon ſuch as ſhall take or exact more then ſhall be therein ſet downe and allowed for time to come.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And as to the trouble and charge which Sheriffes undergoe for leavying of the Kings debts granted to paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, and for collecting the Fines, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, Amerciaments, and other the Kings caſuall Revenues granted in Farme, whereof the Farmers take the benefit, paying a certaine Rent to the Crowne: That either ſome courſe may be taken that the ſaid Farmers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees may make ſome fit allowance to the Sheriffes for their trouble and charge therein, or that his Majeſty may take the benefit of the Revenues of that nature in kinde, as they ſhall ariſe and grow due as was formerly uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the granting of the ſame in Farme. It being obſerveable that both Iudges and Iurors have been diſcouraged to puniſh offenders when their Fines and Forfeitures come not to the King but
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99762:45"/>to private purſes; and ſo Iuſtice is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times left undone to the incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of offenders, or the mercy of the King (where mercy is to be ſhewed) put into a wrong hand.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And as to the injury and loſſe which <hi>Sheriffes</hi> have had by reaſon of fundry grantes made of the <hi>hundreds, Wapentakes</hi> and <hi>Gaols</hi> parcell of their <hi>Bayliwicks.</hi> This will alſo require a preſent reformation, and as it will bee very juſt to right the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> herein, ſo it will be of no great difficulty, if the Law may take place: for that there are ſeverall Acts of Parliament in the time of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. that no <hi>Hundreds,
<note place="margin">Stat. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis 2. &amp; 14. E. 3.</note> Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes</hi> or <hi>Gaols</hi> which were then parcell of their <hi>Bailiwicks</hi> ſhould be at any time ſevered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, but that all grants of that nature ſhould be void. And there is no doubt but the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> might by force of the ſaid Statutes have righted themſelves herein before this time, but that they have ſo ſmall a continuance in their Office.</p>
               <p>But before I leave this point, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be rightly underſtood, for that it is not intended by this reſumption of <hi>Hundreds</hi> or <hi>Wapentakes</hi> that any Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99762:45"/>or Wapentakes ſhould bee reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which at the time of the making of thoſe <hi>Statutes,</hi> were the inheritance of any <hi>Biſhop, Abbot, Lord,</hi> or other perſons whatſoever, and ſo continues at this day in the heirs or purchaſers thereof, by diſcent or meane convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: nor that any ſuch <hi>Hundreds</hi> or <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentakes,</hi> as were then the inheritance of any perſon or perſons as aforeſaid, and are ſince come to the Crowne, by the Statutes of <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> or the <hi>Attainder</hi> of any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſons, their heires or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, or by any gift, grant or exchange from them or any of them; for that in all theſe caſes, if any grant be ſithence made from the Crown to any perſon or perſons, of any ſuch <hi>Hundreds</hi> or <hi>Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes,</hi> it may bee lawfull for the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, and thoſe under whom they claim, to enjoy the ſame at this day againſt the <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> notwithſtanding the ſaid <hi>Acts of Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now for concluding of this point concerning the righting of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes,</hi> in all the former or any other particulars wherein they are wronged, hindered or vexed in paſſing their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99762:46"/>compts, or in the execution of their <hi>Offices,</hi> I conceive it would be the beſt way that ſome Bill were drawne in Parliament for remedy thereof. And that in the ſame Bill the two ancient and excellent <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer</hi> formerly remembred, <hi>viz.</hi> that of 51. <hi>H.</hi> 3. and that of 10. <hi>E.</hi> 1. concerning the manner of paſſing Accompts, and charging and diſcharging of the Kings Rents and Debts, in the <hi>Annuall</hi> or <hi>great Roll</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the like, may bee renewed and explained. And that according to the ſaid <hi>Statute</hi> of 10. <hi>E.</hi> 1. all Rents &amp; Debts whereof there is hope that ſomething ſhall be anſwered for avoiding of all confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and double charging thereof, bee onely charged in the ſaid great Roll, whether the ſaid Rents bee paiable <hi>ad Ret. Scaccar. tantum, ſeu ad Ret. Scaccar. ſeu ad man. Vic. ſeu ad man. Ballivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vel Receptorum.</hi> And that the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ffes</hi> may bee enjoyned thereby to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ready and full payment yearly at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceipt of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be appointed by warrant of the <hi>Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor,</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or any three of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99762:46"/>them (whereof the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> to be one) of all their Receipts of all ſuch ſummes of money ariſing of the ſaid Rents &amp; Farms, being due at or before the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> yearly, at the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> then next following at the furtheſt; and where they bee due at <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> thoſe Rents to be paid before the <hi>Nativity of S. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> at the furtheſt. And where they be due at or before the Feaſt of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangell, thoſe to bee paid at the Feaſt of the <hi>Nativity of our Lord God</hi> then next following. And ſuch Rents as ſhall be due at the Feaſt of S. <hi>Martin,</hi> in the Winter, yearly, thoſe to bee paid at or before the firſt of <hi>February</hi> at the furtheſt: And for default of ſuch pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (being thereof lawfully convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted before the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi>) to forfeit to the Kings Majeſty,
<note place="margin">Sta. anno 7. E. 6.</note> his heires and ſucceſſors (as in like caſes hath been ordained) <hi>two pence</hi> in the pound, in the name of a paine for every day that the ſaid money ſhall bee unpaid after the ſaid ſeverall Feaſts, or dayes of payment, &amp;c. And that ſuch <hi>Farmers, Leſſees,</hi> and <hi>Tenants</hi> as ſhall not either pay to the ſaid <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99762:47"/>Deputy or Deputies (lawfully requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame) all ſuch <hi>Rents</hi> &amp; <hi>Farms</hi> as ſhall be due and payable by them to the Kings Majeſty, his heires, &amp;c. at or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any of the ſaid Feaſts, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, yearly, or bring and pay the ſame wholly into the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſeverall dayes and times after every of the ſaid <hi>Feaſts</hi> ſo formerly limited and appointed, at the furtheſt; and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof lawfully convicted before the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi>) ſhall in like manner forfeit to the Kings Majeſty, his heires, &amp;c. for the non-payment thereof,
<note place="margin">Anno 33. H. 8. cap. 39.</note> (as in like caſes hath been alſo ordained) <hi>two pence</hi> in the pound in the name of a payne for every day after the ſaid ſeverall dayes of payment, until they ſhall pay and ſatisfie what was then due together with the ſaid paines, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And that the <hi>Clerke of the Pipe,</hi> and <hi>Controller of the Pipe</hi> for the time being, together with ſuch <hi>Auditor</hi> or <hi>Auditors</hi> for every <hi>Shire, City</hi> and <hi>Towne Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</hi> and ſuch other officers as the <hi>Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, Vnder-Treaſurer,</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> or any three of them, (whereof the Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> to bee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99762:47"/>one) ſhall thinke fit to appoint,
<note place="margin">Star. anno 51. H. 3.</note> ſhall once every yeare about the Feaſt of S. <hi>Margaret</hi> (being in <hi>Trinity Terme</hi>) make a true and perfect declaration to their Lordſhips in writing under their hands, of all and every particular charge, times of payment and diſcharge in each <hi>Sheriffes Accompt,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: and of all and every other thing concerning the promiſes; and which of the ſaid <hi>Sheriffes, Farmers,</hi> or <hi>Leſſees,</hi> are behinde with their payments: ſo as preſent order may bee taken for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame, together with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid paines which ſhall bee ſo due by them, and the ſaid <hi>Lora Treaſurer,</hi> &amp;c. to aſſigne what ſummes of money due to any perſon or perſons for <hi>Annuities, Pentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or Corodies,</hi> going out of any the premiſes, charged upon the Accompts of <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> ſhall bee paid by the ſaid <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> and which of them ſhall bee paid out of the Receipt of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> as to their Lordſhips ſhall bee thought meet.</p>
               <p>And if ſome ſuch Bill as this may be paſſed, for ſecuring the Kings Rents to bee yearly paid upon ſuch paines as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: And that the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> (paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99762:48"/>their accompts in due time) may be eaſed and righted in the former par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and have three pence in the pound out of all ſuch rents as they ſhall bring in, and twelve pence in the pound for debts, as they have formerly had, his Majeſtie will be duly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Revenewes with much more ſecurity, &amp; at a far leſſe charge then he now is: And the high <hi>Sheriffes</hi> Office, which for its great charge and trouble, hath been of late yeares ſo much avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, will regaine its ancient credit, and encourage men of good ability and quality to take upon them the under Sheriffes place.</p>
               <p>But here I am admoniſhed to make anſwer to ſome objections againſt the credit of the ſaid <hi>great Roll,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in the Pipe.</note> which in all times (as hath been formerly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) hath been of ſo great eſteeme for the ſafe <hi>conduct</hi> of the Revenues of the Crowne, into the <hi>Receipt</hi> of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer:</hi> which exceptions are, That divers good <hi>Farmes</hi> and <hi>Debts</hi> there in charge, and (amongſt many others) a great Fee Farme rent of 180l'. <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> odde money for the Manor of <hi>Crowly, &amp; al. Com. Leic.</hi> due for the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99762:48"/>ſecond yeare of his now Majeſties reigne, together with divers other Rents and Debts, as well in the ſaid <hi>great Roll,</hi> as in the <hi>Recuſants Roll</hi> being taken in charge, by ſeverall <hi>Sheriffes</hi> (amounting to a great value) have been by the <hi>Cerke</hi> of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, poſted of <hi>de anno in annum,</hi> and prolonged without any juſt ground or other legall warrant at all, and that many other abuſes againſt his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> Subjects had bin committed in the ſaid <hi>office,</hi> which in truth cannot be denied: For that they are extant upon Record in a Bill exhibited to his Majeſty, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Clerke</hi> of the <hi>Pipe</hi> by the Kings late <hi>Attorney Generall.</hi> And though they were committed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, yet have they (by the help of that Roll ſo as is aforeſaid by the wiſdome of our Anceſtors ordained for a cotrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) beene diſcovered and brought to light, and ſuch uſe hath been already in part made of that diſcovery for his Majeſties ſervice, and more like to bee as may be very advantagious both for the King and Common-wealth, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the like abuſes for time to come</p>
               <p>But what ſpeake we of abuſes?
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99762:49"/>
                  <hi>Quae Regia in terris?</hi> what Country, what government, what <hi>Guild</hi> never ſo wiſely founded or ſtrongly ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with wholſeſome Lawes is free from ſome ſtaines and corruptions? <hi>Quid non mortalia pectora?</hi> What will not covetouſneſſe and ambition attempt where there is no Law to puniſh? And where the Lawes are not put in execution, it is all one as if there were no Law; as is exemplified by the <hi>Frogs</hi> inſulting upon <hi>Aeſops</hi> log. So as abuſes being the faults of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (and not of the foundation) will grow like ill weeds in every Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and Government, unleſſe they be looked unto and weeded out by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lawes in execution againſt them: but <hi>veritas odium parit,</hi> men will bee wary how they pull an old houſe upon their owne heads, or provoke a neſt of waſpes leſt they be ſtung them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And for that cauſe many men wanting that courage which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> in the Common-wealth by God himſelfe, will rather thinke it better for them to ſleepe in a whole skinne (as they call it) and make <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99762:49"/>then to diſcharge the duty of their oathes: Howbeit for my owne part I was reſolved in ſuch a caſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to runne all the hazards of envy (which I expected and whereof I have had ſufficient experience, and ſtill expect more) then to bee wanting in the diſcharge of ſuch a duty to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> which in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I am bound unto, and thereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make my ſelfe equally liable to the ſame puniſhment with the offendor, which by the foreſaid Statute of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is to be inflicted upon the Superviſors for their <hi>conſent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stat. ann 51. H. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now if after all this, (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the former reaſons and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practiſe of former times) it ſhall at this day be thought any waies tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or fit on the behalfe of the King and Common-wealth, that the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Kings lands now in charge before his Majeſties <hi>Auditors</hi> amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the whole to <hi>one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds per annum,</hi> or thereabouts, and conſiſting at this preſent (for the moſt part of <hi>Fee Farmes</hi> and <hi>certaine Rents</hi>) ſhould ſtill bee continued in the new way out of the old Channell, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99762:50"/>be brought in by <hi>Receivors</hi> and <hi>Bayliffs</hi> as they now are at ſo great a charge and hazard by keeping ſo many hands in the Kings purſe, I conceive the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs nor any other officer (that hath not ſome aime at his owne private benefit more then his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> ſervice) will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the alteration thereof for any ends of his own or any ill will to thoſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but freely to leave it to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the King and his great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: who have declared their purpoſe for eſtabliſhing and ordering the <hi>Kings Revenue,</hi> and for redreſſing the <hi>abuſes of Officers,</hi> and cutting off all <hi>ſuperfluity of expences</hi> concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>But if the ſaid <hi>ſuperfluous officers</hi> ſhall be diſpenced withall to continue, then that it may be with the cautions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Receivors</hi> may bee yearly ſworne to their Accompts in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> according to the ancient uſage and ordinance in <hi>An.</hi> 1 <hi>Mariae Regine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That their accompts (after they are declared and entred with both the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers</hi>) be by the twentieth of <hi>March</hi> yearly delivered into the <hi>Pipe</hi> for further <hi>proces</hi> to be made thereupon
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99762:50"/>for the <hi>ſupers</hi> and <hi>debts</hi> therein depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding according to the ſaid <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hil. Rec. ex parte Rem. Theſ. an. 1 Mariae Art. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And no meſſengers to be hereafter imployed about the ſame for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons formerly alledged.</p>
               <p>As alſo that no proces bee made by the <hi>Treaſurers Remembrancer</hi> for any <hi>Debts</hi> or <hi>Arrerages</hi> ſuppoſed to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending in any of the ſaid <hi>Accompts</hi> by any <hi>Conſtats</hi> or <hi>Certificates</hi> from the <hi>Auditors,</hi> but from the Accompts themſelves, ſo as they may bee under the ſame controlment as before, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, that all the ſaid <hi>Receivors Tallies</hi> be joyned and allowed upon Record as all other <hi>Tallies</hi> are or ought to be.</p>
               <p>It now remaines that I ſhould brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe the principall cauſes which have hindred and retarded the due anſwering of the Kings Revenues and Debts: occaſioned the trouble and grievance of his Majeſties Subjects, &amp; made the bulk of the ſaid Revenues &amp; debts now in arreare to be ſo great.</p>
               <p>And firſt, as I formerly obſerved, one bauſe is, for want of putting the ſaid <hi>Statute</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer, An.</hi> 51. <hi>H.</hi> 3. in due execution by injoyining the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99762:51"/>Sheriffes at their <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Michaelmas proffers</hi> to bring in and pay ſo much of the Rents and Debts ſent forth unto them in the <hi>Summons</hi> of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> as they then had or might have leavied: for the better effecting whereof, the Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> were anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently preſent at the ſaid <hi>Proffers,</hi> and is now perſonated by the <hi>Puny</hi> or <hi>Curſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Baron</hi> onely without any other of the great Officers or Barons to give countenance and aſſiſtance to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: And for that there hath not been a view made yearly to the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> &amp; <hi>Barons</hi> by the Officers of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> of what was anſwered by <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, Farmers</hi> and Accomptants, and what was in Arreare and by whom, according to the foreſaid <hi>Statute</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſecond cauſe is, in that <hi>Sheriffes</hi> have not (according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer</hi>) been ſtrictly holden to their <hi>Appoſalls</hi> at their dayes of prefixion; and for that many of them have beene ſuffered with ſo much impuniy to depart the Court in contempt of the ſaid Court before they perfect their Accompts. The <hi>Treaſurer</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99762:51"/>and <hi>Barons,</hi> being by the ſaid Statute of 51. <hi>H.</hi> 3. to be charged by oath not to attend to heare the <hi>Pleas</hi> of other men whileſt they have to doe with the Kings owne debts.</p>
               <p>A third cauſe is, in that the goods &amp; lands of ſuch Sheriffs which are in the caſe of contempt, as aforeſaid, &amp; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the paſſing of their accompts in due time, have not been according to the ſaid ancient courſe, ſeized into the Kings hands, <hi>Nomine diſtrictionis,</hi> And for that they or their under Sheriffes have not been taken into the cuſtody of the <hi>Marſhall,</hi> before they depart the Towne, or committed to the <hi>Fleet,</hi> (as heretofore in ſome caſes of neglect and contempt, hath been uſed) untill they paſſe their accompts, and anſwer the moneyes due thereupon: As alſo for that in ſuch caſes of contempt, when a <hi>Serjeant at Armes</hi> is ſent for the high Sheriffe, hee continueth them his cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents from Terme to Terme, and doth not bring up their bodies to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Ward, till they paſſe their accompts, as hee ought to doe.</p>
               <p>A fourth cauſe is, In that the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe (contrary to the foreſaid Statute of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99762:52"/>
                  <hi>Rutland</hi>) have been compelled to take into their charge divers dead <hi>Farmes, Seizures</hi> and <hi>deſperate Debts</hi> (being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together illeviable, or for which there is ſome juſt matter of diſcharge) for which they are nevertheleſſe driven to procure diſcharges <hi>de anno in annum,</hi> upon their accompts, to their great dammage and trouble, and their great hindrance to paſſe their accompts in due time. As alſo for that to the like trouble and dammage of Sheriffes, the Farmes and Rents granted in Joynture to the Queenes Majeſty; and other like Farmes granted for tearme of life, or years, <hi>abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> computo,</hi> have not bin remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the ſaid <hi>annual Roll</hi> into a <hi>Roll</hi> of <hi>Reverſions,</hi> or <hi>Exannuall Roll,</hi> till they fall againe to the Crowne; by which meanes the ſubject alſo is dubly vexed, both by the Queenes and the Kings Officers, for one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>A fifth cauſe is, In that all Debts and Farmes in the <hi>Pipe,</hi> which are not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered after one <hi>Summons,</hi> have not (according to the ſaid ancient courſe) been duly put into <hi>Scedula Pipe,</hi> for ſtronger <hi>proces</hi> to bee thereupon made by the <hi>Treaſurers Remembrancer</hi> for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99762:52"/>in the ſame: but ſome of them continued to be ſtil written in the <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> of the <hi>Pipe,</hi> to the great trouble of the Sheriffes, and little or no fruit at all to the King.</p>
               <p>A ſixth cauſe is, in that divers good Rents and Debts have for ſome private ends been ſuffered to bee poſted off, <hi>de anno in annum,</hi> and diſcharged without any good matter of <hi>Record,</hi> or other le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall warrant, by means wherof the ſaid rents and debts, either grow deſperate, or be made fit ſubjects for ſuiters to beg from the King. And for that many Sheriffes have been caſt out of Court, and ſuffered to depart before they pay in their <hi>debets</hi> in the <hi>great Roll</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants Roll;</hi> As alſo for that the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls</hi> of the <hi>Chancery,</hi> have not been yearly ſent into the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſo timely as they ought, nor the Roll of the Inrolments of Leaſes which paſſe under the <hi>Exchequer Seale,</hi> made up and Ingroſſed by the <hi>Clerke of the Pipe,</hi> in due time as it ought to be, for charging all new Rents and Fines in the ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Roll,</hi> reſerved upon any new grant or demiſe from the Crowne.</p>
               <p>A ſeventh cauſe is, In that where the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99762:53"/>the Sheriffes doe not good execution upon the <hi>Writs</hi> ſent forth by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers</hi> upon <hi>Scedula Pipe,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (as they ought) the <hi>amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for their neglects and contempts therein, have not been preſently drawn downe into the <hi>Pipe,</hi> and ſent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe for leavying thereof in <hi>Terrorem</hi> of all other Sheriffes, but ſuffered to ſleep ſometimes for many yeares, or to bee taken off or compounded for ſome ſmall matter to the King.</p>
               <p>An eight cauſe is, In that Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have not been awarded out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> according to the foreſaid Statutes of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>Anno</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. for inquiry to be made into the <hi>Accompts</hi> and <hi>Receipts</hi> of <hi>Sheriffes</hi> and other <hi>Accomptants,</hi> to the end the King may bee recompenced, and the ſubject relieved, in all ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where it ſhall bee found, that the ſaid Sheriffes have defrauded the King, or abuſed the Subject.</p>
               <p>A ninth cauſe is: In that the <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the Revenue have not (as hath beene formerly obſerved) according to the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the ſaid Ordinance of <hi>Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99762:53"/>Articulo</hi> 9.) delivered ingroſſed in parchment the Accompts of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Receivors and Bayliffes of the ſaid Revenues into the Pipe every yeare yearly by the 21. of <hi>March,</hi> ſo as <hi>Proces</hi> might in due time be made from the ſaid <hi>Accompts</hi> to the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> for all <hi>debts</hi> &amp; <hi>ſupers</hi> therein depending againſt the next <hi>liberate</hi> or <hi>ſealing</hi> day of the <hi>Exche.</hi> but have for ſome private reſpects here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and ſtil kept the ſaid accompts in their owne hands (ſome whereof are ſaid not to be ingroſſed for many years together) by which means many great <hi>Arrerages</hi> of <hi>Rents</hi> &amp; <hi>Supers</hi> have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſleyt in the ſame <hi>accompts</hi> for 10, 20, 30, years, &amp;c. before they were written forth in <hi>Proces,</hi> which hath not onely occaſioned great loſſe to the Crowne, but many grievances to the Kings Subjects by ſeiſing the lands which they purchaſed for valuable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaid debtors, for which if proces had been made in due time, they might have bin paid by the debtor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, &amp; a great part of the ſaid arrerages recovered, which by reaſon of long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance becomes deſperate, as in the foregoing diſcourſe hath been obſerv'd.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99762:54"/>
               <p>In like manner it may be here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that by the like omiſſion of <hi>Stewards</hi> of the Kings Manors to ſend up the double of their <hi>Court Rolls</hi> to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to be kept in the <hi>Treaſury</hi> there, as well for the King and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects evidence as that it may appeare what each <hi>Bayliffe</hi> is to bee charged withall every yeare for fines upon Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py-holders, and other profits of <hi>Courts,</hi> according to the ſaid Ordinance of <hi>Anno primo Mariae;</hi> many great loſſes to the crown, &amp; inconveniences to the ſubject, have been occaſioned, there being but few ſuch Court Rolls or any entries thereof to be found which are now extant, either in the times of the late <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> or the late King <hi>Iames.</hi> And that there hath beene the like neglect of ſending up <hi>Rentalls</hi> of the Kings Manors, which once every ſeven yeare are to be renewed by the Steward upon preſentment of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> and to be returned up and ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid <hi>Treaſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A tenth cauſe is: In that the <hi>Eſtreats</hi> of the <hi>Fines, Iſſues, Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and other <hi>Forfeitures,</hi> ſet, loſt and forfeited before the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99762:54"/>
                  <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas, Juſtices of Aſſize</hi> and <hi>Gaole Delivery,</hi> and <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace,</hi> &amp;c. commonly called <hi>Green-wax,</hi> have not been certified into the <hi>Exchequer</hi> in ſuch ſort as by the Lawes and <hi>Statutes</hi> of this Realme they ought to be; but have been <hi>obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, diverted</hi> or <hi>ſuppreſſed,</hi> contrary to the ſaid Lawes, to the encouragement of offendors, and the great prejudice of the Crowne, whereof divers inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in that kinde were lately made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords Commiſſioners for the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> whereby it appeared, that ſundry recognizances and fines forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and impoſed at the Aſſizes and Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the Countrey, in caſes of great and <hi>Criminall</hi> offences and miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, had been ſome yeares ſince remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Cerciorari</hi> into the <hi>Crowne office,</hi> and both theſe and many others of the like nature kept backe and ſtopped there and in other places, which were never certified into the <hi>Exchequer</hi> as they ought to bee, which every way turnes to his Majeſties great prejudice, and loſſe: whether they be pardoned or ſuppreſſed: For that if the King pardon or give them away, the <hi>Farmers</hi> of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99762:55"/>
                  <hi>Green-wax</hi> will looke for a <hi>Defalcation</hi> out of their Rent, of ſo much as they amount unto, by reaſon of a covenant from his Majeſty, that hee will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pardon nor give any of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way during their terme, unleſſe it be by a generall <hi>Pardon</hi> in Parliament. In which caſe it had been much better for the King, they had beene altogether ſuppreſſed and loſt, then to be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or given away, but by a generall pardon in <hi>Parliament.</hi> In conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, &amp; of the inconveniences formerly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, by letting the <hi>Green wax</hi> to farme, and that the <hi>Fines</hi> in the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> are like to be increaſed by putting downe of the <hi>Star-chamber-Court,</hi> ſome compoſition may be made with the Farmers (as the caſe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) and preſent order taken as well for reſuming the ſaid Farmes of the <hi>Green-waxe</hi> into his Majeſties hands; as for the reforming of ſuch abuſes as tend to the ſuppreſſing or diverting any of the ſaid <hi>Greenwax</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But then in caſe of ſuch reſumption I cannot (in my duty) but make ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the complaints of the great abuſes and diſorders which were
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99762:55"/>committed in the managing of the ſaid Revenue when it was in the Kings hands, by the practice of ſome inferiour Clerks and Bailiffes, &amp;c. As namely,</p>
               <p>That where divers iſſues were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreated againſt Sheriffes out of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Courts, <hi>Quia non habuit corpus,</hi> and againſt Noblemen and others, for not appearing at the ſuits of divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either for payment of money ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Bond, or upon actions of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt <hi>detin.</hi> or the like. (In which caſes the Plaintiffes could have no procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings at Law for recovering of their rights, or what was due unto them, without an appearance: and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreating of the ſaid <hi>Iſſues</hi> to be levied for the Kings uſe, being the <hi>Coertion</hi> appointed by the Law to procure ſuch <hi>Appearances,</hi>) the ſaid Iſſues were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe by the undue practices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, upon ſome ordinary ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, procured to bee diſcharged or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpited till a generall <hi>Pardon,</hi> or compounded for ſome ſmall matter; which in no ſort ought to have been done by the Lawes of the Kingdome, before certificate had been made, that appearance was given to the Plaintiffs
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99762:56"/>action, or the debt ſatisfied, &amp;c. to the utter ſubverſion of juſtice.</p>
               <p>And the like abuſes were committed in procuring diſcharges for <hi>Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances</hi> of ſuch parties as had beene bound over with Sureties to the <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes</hi> or <hi>Seſſions</hi> for keeping a baſtard childe, or for performing ſome other publicke ſervice in the Countrey, or upon ſuſpition of Felony, &amp;c. and the like, without procuring any certificate from the Juſtices, or Countrey, that the Pariſh was diſcharged, the ſervice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or what the cauſe was for which every ſuch <hi>Rccognizance</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came forfeited; inſomuch as the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſort, that could uſe no meanes for their diſcharge, were (for the moſt part) left to bee written for; who if they had but a Cow, or any poore U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſills, were driven from time to time, to make their peace with the <hi>Sheriffes Bailiffe</hi> in the Countrey, with ſome of their poore eſtate which the ſaid Bailiffes tooke (as it were) <hi>nomine diſtrictionis,</hi> to their own uſe, without anſwering any part thereof to the King, to the greater impoveriſhing, and ſometimes undoing of the ſaid poorer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:99762:56"/>ſort of the Kings ſubjects.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof, and for the better preventing of the like abuſes for time to come, it was in the time of the late King <hi>James,</hi> thought fit by the <hi>Treaſurer, Chancellor, Vnder-Treaſurer,</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">All mens care, no mans care.</note> that there ſhould bee for ever an Officer in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> called, <hi>the Surveyor of the Green-wax,</hi> formerly mentioned, who ſhould take ſpeciall care to ſee the ſaid Revenue better managed, and from time to time to attend the <hi>Court,</hi> and acquaint the <hi>Barons</hi> therewith, as the caſe ſhould require.</p>
               <p>And this was upon the matter agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with an ancient Statute made in <hi>Anno</hi> 27. <hi>E.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Stat. anno 27. E. 1.</note> By which it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that at one time certaine every yeare, one <hi>Baron</hi> and one <hi>Clerke</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> ſhould goe through every Shire of <hi>England,</hi> to examine and view the Acquittances of Sheriffes and their Bailiffes, touching <hi>Green-wax,</hi> and to inroll them: and alſo to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine complaints made againſt She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, and their Clerks and Bailiffs, that had been done concerning the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the offenders to bee grie vouſly
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:99762:57"/>puniſhed. It being conceived, that the diſcontinuance of that good ordinance had occaſioned the many abuſes and grievances aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, the remedy for preventing the like abuſes and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors in generall, (both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King and his Subjects) for time to come, is, That ſpeciall care bee taken to ſee that the ancient courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the Lawes of the Kingdome formerly mentioned for the better and more timely and husbandly anſwering, and the more due and legall charging and diſcharging of the Kings Revenues, bee ſtrictly obſerved and kept, and to ſee, that due puniſhment be inflicted upon the violators there of accordingly. As alſo to ſee, that all thoſe fore-going cauſes which hinder the Kings ſervice therein, and the quiet of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> ſubjects be removed: And eſpecially that the <hi>Sheriffe</hi> in his yeare, according to his <hi>Proces</hi> ſent unto him out of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> in the Lent <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and Summer <hi>Vacation</hi> (without any reſpect of perſons) doe his uttermoſt to levie all ſuch debts and ſummes of money as ſhall be ſo written to him as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99762:57"/>a foreſaid. And yet where I ſay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, I deſire to bee rightly underſtood, that the perſons of all the <hi>Engliſh Nobility</hi> and their <hi>Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Barons</hi> and <hi>Baronneſſes</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from all arreſts for the Kings debts, as by the Prerogative Writ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, may appeare: And ſo are the perſons of all and every the Knights and Burgeſſes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe of Parliament, ſo long as the Parliament continues. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (in my beſt underſtanding and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation) I doe not finde but the Rents and Debts due to the King, have in time of Parliament been levied by Sheriffes, upon the iſſues and profits of their lands and goods.</p>
               <p>Moreover, foraſmuch as the Kings Majeſty, his Heires and Succeſſors, may be much hindred by the negligence and connivence of the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> by reaſon of a late <hi>Statute,</hi> made in the one &amp; twentieth year of the reigne of the late <hi>King James,</hi> whereby it is provided, that all and every <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe</hi> and <hi>Sheriffes</hi> within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> their Heires, Executors and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99762:58"/>and their Lands, Goods and Chattels, ſhall bee abſolutely diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all and all manner ſumme and ſummes of money which hee or they ſhall leavie or receive, unleſſe ſuch Sheriffe or Sheriffes ſhall bee called in queſtion for ſuch ſumme or ſummes of money pretended to bee leavied and received by them, or any of them, and not accompted for within foure yeares next after they have finiſhed, or ſhall finiſh their accompts, and had their <hi>Quietus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That for preventing thereof, ſome Act may bee paſſed in Parliament, that where any Sheriffe or Sheriffes which ſince the making of the ſaid Act, or at any time hereafter, have or ſhall procure and obtaine any ſuch <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> by meanes whereof they or any of them are, or hereafter ſhall bee (by force of the ſaid Act) diſcharged or acquitted againſt the King, his Heires or Succeſſors, of, or for any ſumme or ſummes of money by them leavied and not anſwered upon their ſaid accompts, or of, or for any untrue or double allowance upon their ſaid
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99762:58"/>accompts, that in all ſuch caſes the Officer or Officers who have or ſhall make any ſuch <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> and have not, nor ſhall not, within the time by the ſaid Statute limited, by ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or other proceedings in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> called, or call the ſame in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion againſt the ſaid Sheriffes, their Heires, Executors, or their Lands, Goods or Chattels, for preventing the loſſe and prejudice which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may happen to the Crowne thereby, and every Officer by whoſe default any ſuch ſumme or ſummes of money, by force of the ſaid Statute, ſhall bee loſt to the King, his Heires or Succeſſors (being thereof lawfully convicted) ſhall pay and forfeit to the uſe of his Majeſty, his Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, all ſuch ſumme and ſummes of money as the ſaid King, his Heires or Succeſſors, ſhall, or may loſe thereby, to be recovered againſt the ſaid officers their Heires, Executors, Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, their Lands, Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, in ſuch manner and ſort as the ſame might have been recovered by the Lawes and Statutes of this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99762:59"/>Realme, againſt the ſaid Sheriffes, if the ſaid Act had not beene made. And that in all ſuch caſes, where by the Lawes of this Kingdome, and the courſe of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> any Officer or Officers of the ſaid Court, are to deliver any <hi>Accompt</hi> or <hi>Accompts,</hi> into any <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Offices</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Court,</hi> by and at ſome certaine time; ſo as proces may bee made upon ſuch <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> and <hi>Debts,</hi> as are or ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending in the ſame accompts, upon any perſon or perſons: So as for default of their delivering in of any the ſaid accompts in due time, any the ſaid <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> or <hi>Debts,</hi> ſhall be afterwards requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and recovered againſt the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers of the Lands of any ſuch Debtor or Debtors, by whom the ſaid <hi>Supers</hi> or <hi>Debts</hi> were ſo due, or againſt their Sureties, which might have been recovered againſt the ſaid Debtors themſelves, if the ſame accompts had been delivered in due time: that ſuch Officer or Officers ſo making default, in delivering of the ſaid accompts in due time, ſhall and may for their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect therein (being thereof lawfully
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99762:59"/>convicted) be ſubject to diſcharge the purchaſers of the ſaid Debtors lands, and their ſuerties againſt the King, his Heires and Succeſſors, and to ſatisfie and pay what the ſaid principall Debtors ſhould have ſatisfied and paid, in caſe the ſaid Accompts had beene delivered in due time.</p>
               <p>And for that it is found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the <hi>Vnder-Sheriffe</hi> that takes upon him the execution of the whole <hi>Office,</hi> both in attending at the <hi>Aſſizes</hi> &amp; <hi>Seſſions,</hi> and upon other <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> returning of <hi>Iuries</hi> and other <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of the <hi>Country</hi> betweene party and party, cannot (in any ſuch due time as he ought) looke into and attend the levying of the Kings Rents and other the Debts and Duties ſent forth in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to <hi>Sheriffes</hi> by ſeverall <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Diſtringas, Fieri facias, Capias</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> out of the two <hi>Remembrancers Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and by the <hi>Summons</hi> of the <hi>Pipe</hi> and <hi>Greenwax:</hi> ſome ſuch like Act may bee paſſed in <hi>Parliament</hi> for the better expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting of the Kings ſervice, that it may be lawfull to and for ſuch perſon or perſons of ability and ſufficiency as
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99762:60"/>ſhall be hereafter appointed by the <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of every County (for whom he will anſwer) to be his Deputy or Clerke for the leavying of the Kings Rents, and other his Debts and Duties as ſhall be ſo ſent out by the ſaid Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and for executing all ſuch Writs out of both the Offices of the ſaid <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers</hi> as aforeſaid, (and for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſineſſe) may continue in the ſaid Office yeare after yeare, ſo long as hee ſhall be approved of, and allowed by the ſaid Sheriffes as aforeſaid, without incurring any of the penalties and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures provided by the Lawes againſt ſuch <hi>Vnder-Sheriff</hi> or <hi>Sheriffes Clerk</hi> as ſhall remaine in his Office above one yeare:
<note place="margin">Stat. anno 23. H. 6.</note> And that notwithſtanding any former Act, Statute or Ordinance to the contrary heretofore made: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe that ſuch <hi>Vnder-Sheriff, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty-Sheriffe,</hi> or <hi>Sheriffs Clerk</hi> ſhall not thereby be exempted from taking any ſuch oaths, nor from any other penalties which by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme are to be taken or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone by them.
<note place="margin">Stat anno 27. Eliz. 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And in regard all the Sheriffes of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99762:60"/>this Kingdome doe finde themſelves much grieved and damnified by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the foreſaid Statute made in the ſeven and twentieth year of the reigne of K. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. by force whereof they are to anſwer for al ſuch iſſues by them retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt any perſon or perſons their <hi>mainpernors</hi> or <hi>pledges</hi> which ſhall be Nichelled or prove to be illeviable, eſpecially in the caſe of Writs of <hi>Diſtring.</hi> ſent out of the <hi>Excheq.</hi> for the homages &amp; other ſervices of the Kings Tenants: that ſome conſideration may be taken of the ſaid ancient Statute in caſe of the ſaid <hi>Sheriffs</hi> ſo farre forth as may ſtand with Juſtice, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Majeſties ſaid. Rights and Services. And that in further eaſe of Sheriffs, there may be a review of the decree lately procured by the parcell makers for Sheriffs and Lords of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to accompt before them for Felons Goods and other Eſcheats, &amp;c. the ſame being found very grievous and burthenſome to the ſaid Sheriftes, and other his Majeſties Subjects, without any profit to the King.</p>
               <p>And in regard diverſe ancient
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99762:61"/>Farmes and Rents now in charge in the Pipe, and before his Majeſties Auditors for the revenue, and in the Court of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> which by reaſon of ſundry alienations of the lands and hereditaments out of which the ſame are iſſuing, and for divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſes, are now at this day very hard and difficult to be levied, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof many of them are like to bee utterly loſt, unleſſe they may (by ſome good and lawfull wayes and meanes) be revived, and more of them like to be loſt hereafter: That for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy herein, a perfect ſurvey may bee made of all his Majeſties Honors, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, Tenements, Rents and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redaitments in every Shire &amp; Hundred, and what particular Rents and ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces either by way of <hi>Fee, Farme,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in perpetuity, or for <hi>terme of life or years</hi> are anſwered for the ſame: And that inquiſition be made for and concerning all the diſperſed <hi>Rents</hi> which are within the collection of the <hi>Bayliffes</hi> or <hi>Collectors</hi> thereof, and of all other Rents within the collection of Sheriffes, or Receivors generall; and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99762:61"/>of what lands or other hereditaments the ſame are particularly iſſuing, and where the ſaid lands and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe lye, and in whoſe poſſeſſion they now are, and when and how to be paid. And that all good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wayes and meanes may be uſed, as well by the view of ancient Records &amp; Inquiſitions (where any ſuch are to be found) as otherwiſe, for reviving of all decayed Rents belonging to the Crowne: And after the making of ſuch ſurveies, that ſome fit courſe may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed for the better ſecuring of all the ſaid petty and diſperſed Rents (in the charge of the ſaid <hi>Bailiffes</hi> and <hi>Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> of the ſame) from further decay: and for eaſing the King from the great charge and hazard he now undergoes in the collecting thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jtem,</hi> that the ſtate of the Kings Caſtles and Houſes may be ſurveyed, &amp; all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied Caſtles and Houſes not uſeful for further ſervice (if it ſhall be ſo thought fit) converted to the beſt profit, and the Fees for the keeping thereof diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. And whether the like ſurvey may not be made of all the <hi>Forreſts, Parkes, Chaces</hi> and <hi>Warrens,</hi> not as yet diſſafo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99762:62"/>or diſparked, (except ſuch as his Majeſty ſhall reſerve for his royall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) and the waſte number of them to be converted to the beſt profit by the yeare, and to be letten as other lands are, and with like condition, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to every man a recompence for ſuch intereſt as he hath.</p>
               <p>And that the Farmes of the <hi>Vlnages</hi> and <hi>Gaugers</hi> be ſurveied, that it may be knowne what Rent is fit to be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them when the terme expireth.</p>
               <p>Many other parcells there are of the ancient Revenues (being flowers of the Crowne) as the <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Chattels,</hi> of <hi>Felones, Fugitives,</hi> and <hi>Outlawed</hi> perſons; the <hi>petty Fines</hi> and <hi>Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> anciently ſet and affeered in the higher Courts upon the Plantiffes and Defendants, <hi>pro falſo clamore, quia non eſt proſecut. &amp;c.</hi> and the like, whereof little or no profit hath of late beene made to the Crowne, according to the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of the Kingdome; by reaſon whereof divers perſons (finding they may doe it with ſuch impunity) have beene incouraged to violate the Lawes, and to ſet on foot and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſundry unjuſt and vexatious ſuits,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99762:62"/>&amp;c. For remedy whereof, this may alſo be taken into conſideration, and ſome life given to thoſe Lawes in a moderate way, ſo farre forth as may ſtand with his Majeſties ancient Rights, the Juſtice of the Kingdome, and the diſcouragement of ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors for time to come.</p>
               <p>And whereas there remains at this day a great bulke of Arrerages and Debts as well in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> as in the Court of <hi>Wards</hi> and <hi>Liveries,</hi> and in the Court of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> a great part whereof is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be good, (as having beene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſleep through the connivence or negligence of ſome of the Kings Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers) other part thereof is ſuppoſed to be diſchargeable by <hi>Tallies, Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances,</hi> and ſome other good matter, but for want of the ſaid <hi>Tallies,</hi> &amp;c. the Officers cannot diſcharge the ſame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record: and for the reſidue (being the greateſt part of the ſaid bulke) it is conceived they are illeviable, and in a manner deſperate. Therefore that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Commiſſions may bee awarded to faithfull and circumſpect men in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very County for making inquiry into
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:99762:63"/>the ſame, according to the ancient courſe formerly preſcribed, and thoſe that ſhall be found good to be ſpeedily brought in and ſatisfied, and ſuch as have <hi>Tallies</hi> or other legall diſcharges for any part thereof to bring them in for acquitting the ſame upon Record in ſuch manner as by the foreſaid Statutes is provided; and for ſuch part thereof as by the <hi>Acquittance</hi> or <hi>Acquittances</hi> of any <hi>Sheriffe, Bailiffe, Receivor,</hi> or other <hi>Collector,</hi> or by other good proofe ſhall be found to have beene received to the Kings uſe by any of them and concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon their Accompts, the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents to be proceeded againſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the foreſaid Statute of <hi>Weſtmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſt.</hi> the firſt <hi>anno</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 6. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. for terrifying of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from doing the like. And for the reſidue that ſhall be found deſperate, the ſame to be put into ſome <hi>Exannuall Roll</hi> according to the foreſaid Statute of <hi>Rutland,</hi> and to runne no more in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, unleſſe it ſhall appeare that ſome eſtate hath accrewed to any of the ſaid Debtors. And if the ſecurity given by Sheriffes at this day by their recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances in the Kings Remembrancers
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:99762:63"/>Office, with ſuerties, bee not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; they may be ordered to give better ſecurity, as their receipts ſhall grow greater.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I have in theſe ſhort advertiſements (though with much weakneſſe) faithfully delivered the ſumme and ſubſtance of what I have gathered and obſerved from the practice and experience of former times, to bee at this preſent taken into conſideration, for the increaſe and better ordering and anſwering of the Kings Revenues, and the eaſe of his Majeſties Subjects, which may bee of ſome uſe for ſteering a courſe in the anſwering and managing of all the Revenues of the Crowne of what nature ſoever: As alſo for the cutting off all ſuperfluity of expences, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Pentions, Annuities, &amp;c. and for preventing the like abuſes of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, for time to come; It having been alwayes held for a <hi>Maxime,</hi> that be the Kings Revenues never ſo great (as great they had need to bee by reaſon of his great occaſions) yet unleſſe care bee taken that his expences bee ſuited and ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99762:64"/>to thoſe Revenues, &amp; that his <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> bee not purloyned, nor put into broken <hi>Ciſternes,</hi> whereby it may leake out, or run waſte; his Majeſty muſt ſtill be in want.</p>
               <p>That this will bee diſpleaſing to ſome, that make their gaines out of the loſſe and wrongs of the King and his people, I cannot be ignorant; howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I preſume this poore adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement may (in ſome meaſure) be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to all that wiſh well to their King and Countrey, which is the onely motive of my taking this taske upon me.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99762:64"/>
            <head>The Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 5. <hi>line.</hi> 6. <hi>read Eſtreated. page</hi> 8. <hi>line</hi> 1. <hi>Baronibus. p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>the foure firſt dayes. p.</hi> 12. <hi>l. ult. ſummes. p.</hi> 16. <hi>l. ult. in contempt depart the Court. p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>carry by their claimes. p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>caſes. p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>rules. ib. l.</hi> 9. <hi>or,</hi> to be left out. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>in his now Majeſties time,</hi> to be quite left out. <hi>p.</hi> 96. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>Sheriffes and other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptants. p.</hi> 100. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>the Greenwax.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
